so uh
this was the first one
hopefully you can see that there
uh
and it's pretty great looking the the
printer we worked with is local and we
were really able to do like kind of a
it's really good like it just looks
amazing
um
the colors are like really nice it's
hard to show it on camera this camera is
also a bit desaturated but it's just
such high print quality on this thing
they did an amazing job looks it's one
of the best looking graphic novels we
have on the shelf and that's you know
that's all down to the print right i
mean you can
anna does great artwork obviously but
like when you're talking about what the
difference is between what it looks like
on the screen and what it looks like
uh printed it's just how good are those
printers you know and uh they were just
great working with the pre-press and
everything they they like had such good
people and we we went through and like
corrected all this stuff
uh in terms of how to ink it properly um
so it it just ended up being like a a
really great time so we're excited about
doing book two
uh
and
you know
i we're hoping the kickstarter works out
obviously
but uh
you know
if you want to check it out
the link should be down below
oh the jeff and casey show okay yeah we
can talk about that
sure um
actually
we put the kickstarter link in here
people who want to check out the book
uh so the jeff and casey show is has two
problems right now
um
problem number one
is
just that
we
you know
jeff kind of had like
a
so he used to live in seattle right
so we were in the same city all the time
so it's pretty easy to record
he sort of now splits his time uh he
lives part of time in california
uh and part of the time
uh back here
and so it's kind of like hard to sync up
schedules because you know when he's
back here
um only part of the time he's obviously
doing important stuff
and all that and you know especially now
with the fact that rad got bought by
epic and all that stuff there's just a
lot of like
difficulty in scheduling that's one
thing the other thing was coronavirus
right so people were quarantining and
staying at home a lot and and all that
sort of stuff
uh
so you know
should we record more episodes jeff in
case so yes um both of us are vaccinated
both of us try to be pretty careful but
i don't know jeff is
is in contact with more people so i
don't know we could try to be safe but
you get me and him in in
[Music]
you know yelling at the top of our lungs
like we do at the podcast in the same
room together if either of us caught
coronavirus we're accidentally going to
give it to the other person there's
there's no way
around that i mean suppose we could do
the podcast with masks on
but uh you know it's it's definitely a
an issue so
you know
um we'll see we'll get back to it soon
and
you know coronavirus hopefully will
become less of an issue anyway as
treatments you know they're working on
good treatments and stuff for it and i
think they'll probably have you know
better treatments coming up and and so
at some point we could just say like hey
it doesn't matter let's just do it but
we still have that scheduling problem so
you know
when jeff's schedule opens up maybe a
little bit more
uh we'll we'll try to do it for sure
have you looked at twitch's code
i have not uh i assume you're referring
to
[Music]
the uh they had like a hack or something
i i
i know that they did because they sent
out an email i haven't really read the
news on it i think i saw something about
it but um
i know that they did because in order to
stream tonight i had to reset my stream
key because they sent out an email
where they were like
hey
uh you guys got gotta reset all your
stream keys and i'm like okay
um
so i haven't looked at anything uh from
the leak i don't know that i would wanna
ever look at twitch's code because i'm
sure it's pretty special
so i don't want to see that
it'd probably give me nightmares
um and i guess i'm not super concerned
about it
necessarily because
i mean
you know we're we're not a high profile
streamer we we don't
you know
uh
[Music]
you know i'm not afraid someone's gonna
go find out how much uh the handmade
hero stream makes a year because it's
not very much
right um you know i can see why maybe
like people's having people having that
information compromise could could be
kind of a problem right
uh if you were trying to keep that
information secret but but we're we're
not i mean you know i think twitch pays
us something like a thousand dollars a
month
uh
so you know that's information i would
just give out so i i don't really uh
i don't really have too many concerns
about the leak other than
kind of one of the obvious things which
is that like
man like
why do we bother with all this stuff you
know there's like two-factor
authentication and all this crap like
come on man like
i mean no one's ever hacked one of my
accounts
and at this rate i don't know why they
would because
it's all it seems like it's easier
rather than trying to hack one of my
accounts they're they're not even gonna
bother just hack the server right why
would you bother trying to come hack
casey muratory
right when you could just hack twitch
you know
um
so it's getting kind of ridiculous
because practicing your own kind of
cyber security is now becoming kind of a
moot point because at some point all of
the places that you log into are all
hacked so it's like okay great yeah they
they can't compromise
my account specifically but it doesn't
matter because they compromise the whole
server so they effectively got my
account anyway right
so it's just it's just embarrassing
um
it's just embarrassing
yeah i mean you know and and uh strange
zack
exactly like
i mean a low-profile streamer such as
myself or or anything else like you know
like sony was hacked to a while back
right and
you think about the average playstation
user right i mean how how much energy am
i gonna dedicate into securing
my playstation account right i mean who
cares you know yeah good you can you
could go on there and and um
[Music]
and file the refund for cyberpunk 2077
for me right
um
it just doesn't make a lot of sense
because it's like these companies get
hacked and you know your
your account is comparably you know
is is meaningless right your account's
nothing no one cares what what's in that
thing um and so like why do we take all
these steps why do we have all these
passwords like what is the point of this
they hack the whole server what was the
point of any of this stuff why am i
sitting there trying to enter a stupid
password on like a bad like like uh
gamepad keyboard
who is that protecting when the hackers
just hacked the entire system right it's
like you would think by now some of
these companies would would actually
have some reasonable security but but
they definitely don't because every week
it's another it's another thing like
this right like it's it's another thing
every time
uh and it's just you know shows no
[Music]
no sign of letting up so
uh so hass and gds i think you are
working on a web server project what do
you use for data persistence
just files sqlite or your own version of
file system in a single file uh none of
those although it is closest to the last
one
at the moment i am just using raw
writing so basically
you
um
you just write to a raw device directly
right so
so like linux
when you
[Music]
want to access like file
a file handle of a device right you can
just raw write to it if you want to
and i don't know that that's what we'll
actually ship with i'm going to have to
decide this stuff a little bit
soon because it's getting close to the
time when we want to actually put
something up uh and i kind of develop
like
hybrid on windows and linux
and i don't actually know to what extent
some of this stuff works well on linux
or not uh that's
that's the only really tricky spot for
me of doing this server programming is
that you know you're not gonna ship a
windows server
because like
why you know
who's gonna pay microsoft 200
per server
and you know you could have 10 20
servers depending on how you scale up
your system right who's going to pay
microsoft for that crap
when it doesn't do anything right um
so the fact that i'm a game developer
means i'm used to printing on windows
and it's a little bit of a
handicap because it's like well
you know i just don't know all the
esoterica um from linux the way i kind
of do on windows you know on windows if
i want to do something weird i kind of
know like i know how it goes i know some
of the
vagaries of the operating system and it
makes it a lot easier to do to do kind
of weird stuff right whereas on linux
you know i'm like okay you know i can go
read the documentation and it says this
will work
and then maybe i can test it on my
machine but then like i go to deploy it
on whatever centos nonsense or something
um
is on the the server on some server farm
it doesn't work or whatever so there's
there's kind of this whole thing and
that part
um is one of the big things that just
isn't done yet as far as getting our
server stuff deployed uh is figuring out
how that stuff is really going to work
um
and the reason i say that is because
for us
like pricing and what server farms to
use and that sort of stuff has been like
very challenging you know what i'm
saying
um
i thought we were going to be able to
use
uh
like there's a couple places i was like
oh these are pretty low cost places we
can get servers at and they have things
like 10 gigabit per second unmetered
which is kind of what i wanted um but
like you look at this and they don't use
ecc ram so you're like okay that's
probably not great
um and so you kind of go around and
around you're like okay this place looks
pretty good but you know are they too
expensive no all right i guess they're
okay and how how's it gonna deploy
so i don't know there's a lot of ways
you can go with this stuff and it's and
it's again the problem there is mostly
just that you know i'm a game programmer
um
the web server
side of things is not hard for me from a
programming standpoint because all the
things that are involved i've done
before but the platform stuff is not and
so it's been a bit of a struggle
platform-wise figure out like how are we
going to get these servers where are
they going to be and who's going to host
them and how much they're going to cost
what is the realistic
actual like performance of these data
center things you know like
a perfect example would be if i'd done
this a bunch of times before where i'd
like deployed
you know custom server infrastructures
before
um i would just know a few things like
one of the things i would know is
a few data centers i'd worked with
before
what actual throughput do you get
right like like if you buy a 10 gigabit
per second
uh uplink from such and such data center
what do you actually get right because
you see all these things like oh this is
10 gigabit second guaranteed or this is
five gigabit per second guaranteed or
whatever yeah i don't know what they
actually mean by that right you know
it's it's the kind of thing that people
fudge the numbers about and
or you know it's not exactly entirely
above board or those sorts of things so
so i do think that like to a certain
extent
um
you know there's going to be some
growing pains the end of this year is
going to be pretty rough for me i think
because as i try to put this stuff
online and actually get it battle
hardened i'm sure i'm going to have
um a lot of issues with things don't go
the way i thought they would because
what you know is said
um in documentation or on people's
websites or whatever isn't really what
happens right and those are the kinds of
things that once you've been able around
the block a few times you you know
but until then you haven't
so strange accident had a good
experience with ovh 10 uh gb line so
that's great information
um thank you for saying that like that's
i'll check that out i know who you're
talking about um
[Music]
hearing stuff like that's just useful
for me right like hearing that people
did such and such and and had a bad
experience or had a good experience it's
just it's just useful right
uh
one of the other things i considered
doing just building our own machines and
mailing them to data centers right but i
just felt like that might be too much
variability there and too much back and
forth oh you know what's the which power
supply do you need to use for this data
center and
oh it got it got dropped in shipping and
now the machine doesn't work and you
know
so i i just
there's so many ways you can deploy a
server architecture nowadays it's like
writing the server architecture is very
difficult
certainly
but it's the part that i understand
right getting the actual hardware you
know
um
is
is like a new part for me because it's
just not something i've done
and uh so i'm not looking forward to
that but you know it has to get done and
it has to get done relatively soon so
uh
you know i'll have more to say about
that later you know what exactly we use
uh in terms of of of storing files may
have to change slightly depending
on the circumstance but just raw right
um
is is basically what i wanted to do
because
the reason for that is just i just don't
so
when you're talking about something like
a server the operating system basically
gives you almost zero benefit like like
ideally for something like a web server
there would be no operating system
and
to a certain extent you could do that
right you could write something really
honestly bare metal but the investment
in figuring out how to get all the
driver stuff that you need set up like
in your own custom code and all that
stuff that
that's a pretty
that's a pretty dangerous route to go
down right
um it's not like the old days when
computers were more uniform so you kind
of knew like if we're deploying you know
if if
we're deploying an amiga 500 then we
don't need an operating system because
we could just
implement the the the individual
hardware uh things we need right on
there and it works right
so you know at least for this first
round of deployment um we're we're going
to be sitting on top of linux kernel but
nothing else
and i don't really want a file system
it doesn't do anything for us
it just gets in the way we don't want
metadata we don't want multiple files we
just want
the server to be able to store the data
that it needs it knows where the data is
and it knows how it's organized so it
doesn't want anything other than just a
raw ability to like read and write
sectors ideally knowing how big this the
optimal sector size is even would be a
plus for us
uh because we can't take advantage of it
so like the closer we can get to raw
right the better
but i didn't want to go all the way to
like we're writing the disk driver
because i just felt like that was way
too risky and way too big of a time
investment so we're up one for that but
we'll
go down as far as we can otherwise we
don't really want anything else running
on the system as far as i'm concerned
everything else
um
is just a security headache and a
maintenance headache for me right
anything else that runs on there is just
something i don't really understand i
don't know linux file systems very well
right
so i i would just have as little as
possible um
as close as possible just booting
directly into our code and then just
having the hardware do exactly what my
code says is what i would prefer because
that's gonna be the most secure because
there's not other things running that
people can attack right and it's also
just going to be um the least
maintenance headache because the less
code that's running the less i have to
worry about someone else's code like
breaking or whatever right
so by raw writes what i mean is
um
at least in certain circumstances
depending on on how things are set up
uh you don't actually need the operating
system to
do any kind of
like brokering of where or what you're
writing so so normally what happens
right
when you
there's there's like two levels of file
system maybe we could go to the white
the the light board for this actually
i'll i'll i'll go to light bar for this
let me let me just feel this one other
question that was here
uh someone said not a game dev here but
wanted to let you know that your
approach to software took me out of a
burnout short story long arigato
gozaimasu ah toitashimaste
um
very glad to hear that obviously
uh
so let me go ahead and just and just uh
take take a second to draw it out um
because because i think i can explain
this a little bit better with a diagram
uh if if this is something you're
actually interested in uh it's not a
terribly difficult concept so i should
be able to just you know
say here's roughly what i mean
and hopefully that'll that'll be a lot
clearer than me just kind of saying
stuff here uh if that makes sense
so
um
what happens right
uh if you take a look
if you take a look at what's going on um
in a typical
scenario where you're not really trying
to take control of the system where
you're not trying to be sort of down at
a lower level
uh you typically have like a a tiered
sort of uh for every kind of a file
right that you do you have like a tiered
waterfall kind of thing uh going on so
you know maybe somebody you know calls
like f right you know
um up here at the top level and and this
is in your application so like your
application is got some call uh that's
doing an f right and that f right you
know it has a file handle in it and that
file handle is really just something
that is is going through like a library
probably right i mean at least in the
case of uh f right
so there's a file handle in here
and the file handle is like tracking a
bunch of information it's it's you know
it's gonna keep like a buffer so if you
f write something and it's small it'll
like coalesce it in a buffer right
so this file handle has like a buffer
associated with it probably and so
whatever you write is going to go into
this buffer
eventually it's going to decide to flush
that buffer so when that buffer fills up
or when you close the stream or when you
flush the stream or you know whatever
else the library like whatever the
library wants to do
when this buffer is ready
uh and you know just to make this even
more explicit maybe i can i can draw it
like this so there's a buffer and it's
filling up you ask to f write this piece
of information and it puts it into this
buffer right
so you actually had this piece you put
it down into this buffer now the buffer
has this piece that's going to then
thunk through to like a lower level call
like a syscall on the operating system
or something that's actually designed to
write some data
and there's a couple different ones for
this um but you could think of it this
way as
what you probably have is you have the
os here and this is a syscall
like on linux
so what happens is this buffer now
there's if effectively an interrupt
happens
um that transitions to the os depend
again this is very
os dependent but
on something like linux you're going to
have a syscall occur so it's not really
an interrupt that's the wrong word for
it assist call occurs uh which is an
actual instruction
and the operating system basically wakes
up and takes back control right so in
you know these are happening at a higher
level this this right here is all
happening in some higher level ring
right so this is it some higher level
ring in the processor this is now going
to happen in like ring zero
or something
right so the syscall there's a privilege
escalation when you do this and the
syscall wakes up and it's like oh okay
this person wants to write this buffer
so this buffer is now coming down to
syscall
the problem is
the syscall is really just there to
accept the buffer from you and actually
just put it in another buffer usually
right so what it's usually going to do
is it's going to say okay you know uh
i've got a a disk cache right that's
like backing uh what i write stuff and
you know who knows how big that is but
he told me what the file handle that was
open was because this file handle for
the library had probably another file
handle like a file index
right
like you know 0 1 2 3 4 or whatever that
corresponds to the os so the os got that
and it got the buffer and it's like okay
he wants to use this handle this index
which i know which one that was and he
wants to do this buffer so what actual
file is that let's let's take a look at
what i'm doing cache wise with files and
let me find like the cache location
right
um and that has its own buffer because
remember all disk io on modern operating
systems goes usually through some kind
of a cache you know what i'm saying so
so typically what goes on is you don't
actually write any data yet
your buffer goes into some slot in the
cache right
um where it's like
this is part of a larger piece like i
don't know how big this is i i haven't
looked at the linux kernel
in forever so you know maybe there's a
256k chunk and we only read and write
out those 256k chunks typically or
something you know i don't know maybe
it's only 4k who knows what it is you
can go look that up
the point being they're going to put
your buffer into a
piece of that cache but it's but it's
just going to sit there they're not
necessarily going to write it uh maybe
they're going to assemble some other
rights first um maybe they need to read
out like what was in the other parts of
the chunk into the cache and assemble
this part because it overhangs part of
the like you're like in the middle of
that somewhere who knows right it could
be doing anything again until you if you
don't actually go down and look at what
the os code is doing you know you could
do all sorts of things here
right
um so this is going to happen uh and
even that of course is not actually
the end of it right because because this
is just like some
uh disk you know subsystem right
um but there's still going to be like
one more level like below this one uh
which is like the actual hardware part
right
um and this who knows how this works
like like we have no idea right uh
because it could be who knows what's
what kind of driver you've got who knows
what kind of storage subsystem you've
got
but at some point right there's going to
be a like a hardware layer down here and
there's the actual like there's the
actual drive
right um so we've got a drive here
and it's got some i o system right and
this could be anything it could be the
pci bus in the case of like an nvme um
it could be like an like a sata cable
like right in the case of an ssd drive
like who knows there's some io and it
has to go from here to here somehow
right
so what's gonna happen is eventually
this buffer is going to go into some
kind of a driver layer right
and that driver layer is going to be
responsible this probably was locked in
physical memory so that the like
whatever the driver is can like
communicate the physical memory across
this i o channel right
so this was probably locked in physical
memory some way somewhere it's gonna
like sit there for a little while and
some driver is gonna do something to
like push it out to the drive eventually
and it goes into some chunk like this
250 56k chunk like maps into there right
and if you think about all of this stuff
that has to happen and and i'm like
that's just like the broadest
possible overview right like what i'm
talking about here
is like just the basic overview so it's
a really high level right
if you look at all that stuff that's
happening it's just a tremendous waste
of everyone's time
if you actually could have just done
this yourself right
so if instead of calling some function
that just said i got this little piece
assembled into a buffer so you can pass
it to a buffer so you can pass it to a
driver so the driver can send it over
the pci bus
to a drive or something right
instead of doing all that what we would
rather do
is just re-find out
what the native page size is for this
drive and just give the operating system
direct calls it's like
i'm gonna lock some memory in physical
memory for you
i'm gonna leave it
there until i see this right complete so
i'm just gonna put the whole thing you
need to write you don't need to read
anything
i'm going to put the whole chunk that
you're going to send as an entire chunk
over to the drive
so that there's no middleman right it
could the driver can literally just take
this directly without all these copies
of copies of copies
to get something down to where it needs
to go right
um and incidentally this exact same
procedure is actually not that different
from what happens with a network card
it's a little bit easier um in one sense
in that there's not that sort of random
placement problem of buffers uh onto
places on the drive but it's very
similar in that if you don't use
something like registered i o or stuff
like that
uh
you're you're asking the os though to
like copy it into places where it can be
reached by the actual nick that's trying
to grab it out and all these other sorts
of things right
so the idea uh behind all of this was
like kind of like convenience and making
things look like an old 1970s computer
that was like streaming out data but but
really it's it's not good right um like
you don't want any of this
um and so what you tend to do nowadays
if you actually care about this sort of
stuff which to be fair
web stuff doesn't tend to um you know a
lot of web stuff is just like let's have
a python
interpreter running on top of the c
runtime library running on top of
the os running on top of the driver
right like so you know you wouldn't be
alone if you just call
f right you know like tons of people are
doing that
that's totally standard in the web world
but if you actually care about high
performance
server stuff which some people in the
web world do right some people get paid
a lot of money i would assume at places
like you know google or something
to take uh and try to you know speed up
the like super crappy all the crap that
sits on top try to speed up that bottom
part they would probably care about this
sort of stuff um but you'll see things
like on um
on windows you have like registered o
and you have um some some other things
like there are custom apis for it but uh
you also have on linux there's a thing
that's really good uh it's called iou
ring
um
i don't know if you've ever seen this
this is what what i used
uh for the linux layer
and basically what iou ring is is it's a
way of kind of getting rid of all of
that process
um and it's a way of just writing and
saying look
i don't want to issue syscalls i don't
want to do any of that stuff all i'm
going to do is just get some locked
memory um i should talk about what the
lock memory stuff is
maybe we can do that if anyone has any
questions but i'm gonna get some memory
that's visible to me and the kernel and
the drivers and whatever right and all
i'm gonna do is just write the stuff i
need into that memory
and i'm gonna trust that the kernel will
look at a little ring buffer that tells
it what i want to do and just do it so i
never we're like two separate threads
running in parallel
um so what happens is you have like you
know your app thread
and you could have more than one app
thread obviously but you know at least
one app thread and you have a kernel
thread
and they're running in parallel and what
will happen is the app thread will like
you know it'll like prep some buffers
right so it'll like go okay i got to put
some stuff i want to write out in here
when it's ready right it'll just like
issue
a um a write to memory
and the kernel thread is just looking at
that
memory area right
if this thread was like a sleep
then it is still sort of a cis call you
you have to do like a call that checks
and if the shed was asleep it will like
wake it up or whatever right but if this
thread was busy so let's say this was
busy like processing the last part so
the kernel thread is like processing
some other write you were doing like
getting that ready and handing it off to
drive or whatever
if you write into the memory into the
ring buffer
before it finishes it will just look
here it'll it'll like go okay i'm done
with the last thing i did let me look
and it'll find the next thing to do and
it'll just start doing it so it'll start
processing the next one right so this
one that you prepped it will process
here and of course here it was
processing something you wrote before
and so you can create really high high
bandwidth low overhead
channels between uh the
between the kernel and you
um that don't require these sys calls in
this buffering
so so this is more what i'm talking
about the raw write part of it all i
meant by that was not going through any
file system stuff so so no file system
layer at all you just write crap to the
disk and you pull crap back from the
disk as close as possible as you can get
to that
um and again the reason for that is just
to avoid the overhead of going through a
file simulator because if you're your
own web server what do you need a file
system for right
it's not like multiple people are like
using this machine and and you need you
know someone to be able to talk about
this jpeg that you know they put there
it's like you're the only person running
you're the server who's serving
everything so there's no reason why you
would have to go through some
intermediary to know what like the name
of a file is or where it is or how big
it is because you're the only one who
wrote anything and you're the only one
who reads anything so just keep that
table yourself and you don't have to go
through ext4 or you know refs or
butter fs nowadays on linux i guess
probably
um
so between iou ring and trying as cl
much as possible depending on the
circumstance to just use raw writes to
an unformatted drive with no file system
you can get rid of a lot of crap for me
it's not as much about performance
because i don't know that disk i o i
mean i'll know more when this is
deployed in the wild i don't know that i
haven't been sweating disc io because i
don't know that we really are going to
care that much about disk i o
but for me it's it's not about it's not
about speed it's about reliability the
less of this crap there is the better in
my opinion because linux is just a janky
pile and i don't want any of it running
the kernel may be sort of okay but the
user space definitely isn't so so
ideally i would like to if not in the
first incarnation of our server stuff
because like i said you know you can
only do so much
but i want to minimize it at least and
then going forward i would always want
to remove user space stuff from our
servers until we're basically down to
nothing where it's just our code running
is the only thing running in user space
would be ideal for us because again it
just gets rid of a huge maintenance
headache because none of the linux user
space stuff is good and it doesn't do
anything right if that's for if you're a
user of a machine a web server is
somebody who just wants complete control
over the entire machine
and just uses all the threads to serve
stuff right
it doesn't want
other processes running right there's no
benefit to those other processes if if
your server knows what it's doing in and
has all the features it needs you don't
you don't need those right
um
let me check to see sorry i wasn't
looking at chat there uh does that kind
of make sense
um
there
oh man there's a lot of chat that's good
i guess
um
two
okay so yeah um i've read the sequel
thank you for putting the q colon in
there because the q colon makes it
easier for me to see does the scheme
used here have similarity to command
buffers in gpu also what is the
significance of these apis featuring
cues just storing commands what benefits
does it have um so yes like the the way
you can think about iou ring is very
similar to how you can think about gpu
command buffers they're very very
similar
the primary difference between them
is only that
as far as iou ring is concerned anyway i
don't think there's any chance
at all i mean there may never be any
chance
um but at least currently since iou ring
is very new there's no chance that the
iou ring stuff is getting implemented in
hardware iou ring is more just a way of
packaging a syscall into a ring buffer
so that it can be executed without the
syscall right
um when you think about gpu stuff
depending on what circumstances you're
talking about you could actually be
talking about something that actually
gets executed on the graphics card
now that would be a really cool thing to
happen um
in the in the i o u ring space and there
actually is precedent for that there are
things um like uh
oh what's the name of that stuff
in infiniband so there's things like
infiniband um or other things that are
in the service space that are like
all about like high performance
kernel not involved nonsense to like
communicate between machines and stuff
so there obviously is high-end hardware
that does have some of that stuff but it
doesn't have anything to do with iou
ring as far as i know there's no
integration between those two things
they're just separate like infiniband i
think is a thing where you can basically
say like i want to map this memory
across multiple machines so basically
like it's like a back plane like a back
channel
that'll like sync the memory so if you
write something the other machine will
see the rights like in the data center
right and things like that and again the
point there it's not going any faster
right you're still going over a wire so
it's going the same speed as anything
else but the idea is you can reduce a
bunch of overhead
if there's a piece of hardware sitting
there that's just looking at you know
this this sort of uh mapped memory and
feeding it to other machines really
quickly uh it can get rid of all this
overhead of the kernel ever even having
to know right so
again a lot of this stuff is just about
getting the overhead out of the system
when you ask the second part of your
question which is what is the
significance of these apis featuring
queues
what benefits does it have um that's the
benefit right um so the oops i didn't
mean to do that
i just accidentally locked my own thing
that i was using to the read chat
oops
uh okay um
so the significance there
just to to draw the skin because i
didn't do a very good job drawing that
diagram obviously um because i was
talking about the buffer flow there
uh but if if you think about what
actually occurs when you do one of these
sys calls right so if i want to do
something like a right syscall so you
know i want to do something like a right
not not f right because that's like
one level higher right that's the
buffered version if i want to do
something like a write syscall so i'm
calling linux
and i'm going to actually issue like a
direct write for the syscall and you can
look up in the table there's like a
syscall called right
that's this call
what's going to happen in the assembly
language is you will literally see a
thing that says syscall
there's this is an actual instruction
like on an x86 cpu right
and what the syscall instruction does is
it's basically a transition to the
operating system that's designed to
happen quickly and what happens is the
registers
are the parameters
so what will happen is your code will go
like okay set you know this register to
the file handle set this register to the
address it's registered the size syscall
the operating system goes oh what's
going on oh is this call which syscall
oh i should one other thing was write
which thing you called that's in a
register too you put a number the number
is is which um
operating system function you wanted you
look in the table you'll see like right
is you know seven or something right um
that's how it knows what to do so it
wakes up and goes whoa what's in
register blah oh it's seven i'm gonna do
a right it's it's not seven by the way
i'm making that number up go look at the
table you'll you'll see
um
so it's like okay that's that's what i
needed um
i'll go do that one i'll look at the
other registers find what i need to do
i'll actually process this here
and shove it off and then when i'm done
i'm gonna detransition right i'm gonna
go i took a ring transition down to the
operating system to do the assist call
and now i'm going to transition back to
user space so you're constantly doing
that ring transition which costs right
you're paying for that ring transition
um and not only you're paying for that
ring transition but you might have to
pay for like saving and restoring
registers like all sorts of stuff could
have to happen here because you're
effectively going from your code with
all the registers set to whatever they
are and the memory mapping whatever it
is into the operating system which has
to wake up in the middle of that
no context at all and it has to like go
okay let me like get everything set up
let me handle this thing
all right i'm done now and let's get out
of it right
so
that inefficiency of this of filling out
the register is doing the syscall
and taking that ring transition overhead
where it's like kernel transition and
back kernel transition and back
if you're trying to do a lot of writes
you're just wasting all your time doing
these sys calls like there's no point to
those these things you're just sitting
around doing it you'd like to be able to
start doing them in bulk
that's what iou ring basically gives you
so the reason that these things tend to
look like
a commit a cue and and that's what they
look like by the way so they tend to
look like this
um
these systems tend to look like a a like
an in and an out cue right and they've
got like you know chunks so your
application like it puts something in
here
right and the os reads it and writes the
output here right it like reads writes
reads writes and they don't have to go
in order so you might read these and
like if this one took a really long time
then maybe this one actually goes here
and this one goes here and then this one
actually goes like all the way over here
right
so the reason that these cues work well
is because now you don't need syscalls
at all
right all you do is just slam all your
data into this into this command buffer
and the operating system's just reading
it it you're writing it it's reading it
there's no need for a syscall at all you
can just keep going like that for as
long as you want and the only time you
ever need to make any kind of syscall is
just if you
if you look so i don't
i've never looked at the actual codes i
don't know exactly what they do here on
linux you can check but
if this thread goes to sleep because you
didn't have anything in the queue like
it finished it like red it read up to
here and it goes oh there's nothing i
looked at the the index and and this one
is this is the last one right i don't
need to read anymore they haven't filled
out anything else
it may go to sleep
right
if it goes to sleep you need to wake it
up
so
if that happens then there would be a
cis call to wake that threat up but if
you think about it in that case it's
probably okay because you couldn't have
been doing anything that high bandwidth
if you if you if it underflowed if the
if the operating system like got to the
end it was like i'm done
so in the scenario where you care which
is where you're just writing tons of new
blocks and you just want to slam all
these things into buffer and just like
have the operating system just like
picking them off writing them writing
them writing them right without ever
having to do all these transitions
um
that's the case where you actually care
about avoiding tons of unnecessary sys
calls
uh
and that's where it's you're not gonna
have to make any in the case where this
thread goes to sleep well you couldn't
have been doing that much work anyway
because obviously you weren't calling
this very often because you called it so
a few times that the kernel beat you to
the end of it right
um so
that's one thing you do have to do now i
believe
again i don't remember because i didn't
i don't program linux right
um but you know i had to look at how
they do it because i needed to program
it this one time
i believe the idea would generally be
because in these systems it usually is
you don't call it every time you insert
something either you insert all the
things you want to insert and anytime
you want you can call to check to make
sure the thread's awake so also you can
make sure that you don't tend to like
stutter much because you can make sure
you dump a bunch of stick in there and
stuff in there and then kick it off if
you want to now you don't want to wait
too long because you want the operation
to be like to get overlap but but that's
basically the idea
um and so yeah it's it's exactly like a
gpu in that way um you're just filling
up these buffers so that you can both do
work at the same time right but it's a
little bit unlike a gpu in that in a gpu
expect some of this work to be uh be
done by a processor that's like a sep a
different processor than the cpu
that you're on whereas in um like
something like i o u ring you're
actually talking about the same
processor so you're just talking about
two cores on that processor using this
to avoid having to
um do a bunch of sys calls on the same
core to do this
uh
so off you go there's probably also some
other benefits i don't know i haven't
worked with iou ring
much but you can think about there might
be some other benefits too if the kernel
thread is just doing its thing and your
thread is just doing your thing and
you're on separate cores even then
you're not going to be polluting like
your l1 and l2 caches every time you hit
one of those syscalls anything that the
kernel needs to go touch for pages of
data that need to actually do stuff such
as like ext for pa like like metadata or
butterfs metadata or stuff in the kernel
that it needs to check for permissions
or i don't know right like who knows
what the linux kernel does it's like 30
million lines of code or something at
this point
whatever it's doing in there
if those are on the same
uh core as when you did your syscall
that's polluting your cash right that's
taking up space in your l1 or your l2
whereas if you're two separate threads
on two separate cores each doing your
own thing you'll get a lot better cash
currency because you're just touching
your stuff that's in l1 and they're just
touching their stuff that's in l1 and
you guys are never like fighting over
which cache lines are going to be
resident in your l1 or l2 so it seems to
me and i've never profiled this so don't
you know take that with a grain of salt
but it seems to me that there probably
are other wins you could get there as
well that aren't just about avoiding
like syscall overhead or avoiding um you
know unnecessary buffering and things
like that
but
yeah
okay so there was a question here before
it scrolls off um
in one of your very old handmade hero
episodes you were talking about how you
would like to program on linux but linux
debuggers had always just been worse
than the mediocre visual studios
i do think that using gdp is not
actually great but i'm assuming there
were and are other options can you maybe
go more into depth on what makes
debugging linux that much worse than
using the monstrosity as visual studio
um yeah so actually
when i said debug and layout sucked i
actually meant all of it so
i agree gdb is not great um and to be
clear about that it's it's you have to
be careful when you say gdp is not great
because gdp actually really
i mean i don't i don't like using it and
i don't use it very much so i i can't
say like definitively
but in my experience gdb has a lot of
features
so usually it's not that gdb sucks
because it doesn't do the thing you want
it to do usually it can do whatever the
thing is that you wanted to do and maybe
there's some edge cases there but you
know it's it has a lot of advanced
features gdb
uh the problem is is like the
usability's terrible so you you waste so
much time hunting for bugs with gdb that
you could have just found them easier
some other way like with a printf log or
by just putting in more asserts in your
code or whatever you could have
it's not going to save you time and the
only point of a debugger is to save you
time right i mean most of us would
presumably agree that we will find the
bug eventually because we can put we can
do work in other ways to get to the bug
so it's not like a debugger is the only
thing that can find bugs the point of a
debugger is to find the bug faster if
the bugs are actually getting found
slower when using the debugger that is a
useless utility and gdb to me is exactly
that useless utility with the exception
of just telling you like where your code
crashed if it's zig-zagged or something
um
it really can't
it really can't find bugs faster than
you could find them yourself without it
right and that's why i think it's kind
of crappy
the same tends to be true of almost all
debuggers on linux they're really slow
trying to step through them is arduous
they oftentimes can't display
local variables properly or watch window
stuff properly
most of them can't show disassembly
there's like very few that can actually
disassembly you i mean that's a
very important aspect of a debugger if
you're a serious programmer is to see
the
um
it's just a mess it's just a mess
so i'm actually talking about everything
i tried probably 10 different debuggers
maybe 15
um the last time i looked for one and
they were all universally horrible i
think the thing i ended up using
uh the most was qt creator
uh
which kinda sorta has a debugger that
works um but but it's really bad uh it
was just like the least bad of the like
20 000 like clion and qt creator and
this and cgdb and that
um
i will say that at that time uh nak st
the guy who does the um
essence operating system he recently
wrote a front end for gdb that people
have said good things about and i mean
since he writes his own operating system
you know you kind of know that's a
certain level of conf com
competence as well
so i haven't checked that out yet
when i actually go to do debugging
of some of this stuff on the actual
servers i will probably try to get that
running
because i'll probably need a debugger
here and there
uh when i go to move it from the local
machines to the linux server machines i
anticipate obviously there'll probably
be a lot of of nasty debugging that i
have to do
uh to like get everything
proper but
i i i can't really speak to that because
i haven't tried it but that's on my list
for sure
um
okay what exactly
uh
are we at for questions here
let's take a look
i'm going to take a little sippy poo
here
the mic's a bit hot yeah is it is it uh
too loud
um i assume this one's fine this one
looks fine is it just the other one that
was too hot
i don't so here's the problem i don't
actually think it is too hot i think
there's just a weird clipping problem i
don't know what it is
um it may actually just be obs uh but i
have to root it down there there's
definitely some kind of weird like sound
anomaly and i don't know where it's
coming from
i don't uh it's it's something i got a
root root down but but i don't know that
it's it's the actual uh board mic i can
try
turning the board mic down a little um
and c but i don't know that that'll help
on the topic of syscalls the kernel has
its own address space uh right or is it
just protected
and not accessible from user space can
it copy user memory in
um
so it's kind of the wrong way to think
about it
a little bit so let me just make sure
we're on the same page with that
so memory is just memory
you have physical ram in your machine
and the ram has the data in it
uh
the thing that is different between you
and the kernel
is the mapping
right so your process has a mapping that
says which addresses go with which
physical ram chips right like how do you
you know how do you map them
uh and it has protection bits that says
whether you're allowed to read or write
from them and so on as well right
so
the real way to think about it is that
when you do something like
ask the kernel to do something
it's really the kernel's discretion like
if the kernel wanted to it can just work
with your
you know with your memory layout
the reason that usually something has to
happen there is because the colonel
wants to hide stuff from you
and maybe doesn't want you to know where
things are right so it has to do work
with the setup of the memory page tables
to make sure that you can't
access a page in in physical ram that it
wants
to keep hidden from you right
um
but it's not like you have to copy user
memory in
necessarily the kernel can access your
memory just fine
the reason it may have to copy something
usually is because of some other
constraint
and the other constraint is something
like the following
a
you made a call that appears
instantaneous but it's actually slow
it's actually latent the example like we
gave with write like i'm going to write
this stuff somewhere
well i need the contents of the buffer
that you pass to write i need that to
remain valid until
you actually
until the disk actually finishes
committing it right
so because i want it to appear
instantaneous to the user
i have to copy it out of that buffer
into something that i know will stick
around right
so that's thing one
thing two is the exact same thing is
true
not for the buffer but for the mapping
of the buffer as well so in other words
if the vm system
might wake up in the middle of this
right even if the user promises to not
change the buffer for a while if the vm
system might wake up and change the
mapping of that so that it gets mapped
out of that same physical page well the
problem there is things like the disk
right like like a piece of hardware
it doesn't go through virtual memory
so
when i translated the virtual address to
a physical address to pass it to the
disk
if that then gets moved or whatever
that whole right falls apart right now
it's going to write some other thing
from that same physical rampage that
means something else right
so typically the reason that the copies
happen is not because the kernel
couldn't just read your memory the
colonel can read any memory it wants
right
the problem is actually that the kernel
usually is trying to pretend that
something is instantaneous that's not
and the consequences for that um are
that it has to do a copy to put it
somewhere that's okay right now there's
other reasons for the copy too like i
said one is to assemble buffers that are
the right size for writing to things
like disks so somebody's asked to like
assemble things you can think of this as
very analogous to assembling cache lines
in a cache
like when a cpu a cpu can't write like a
byte of memory right like that doesn't
happen when a cpu tries to write one
byte of memory what actually happens is
that one byte gets assembled into a 64
byte cache line which then gets put out
to the cache which then gets put out to
main memory right
um so there's like these right combining
buffers that are there to assemble right
and the same happens in the os it has to
assemble things that are the correct
size for use with hardware because the
hardware doesn't just arbitrarily take
like individual byte ranges and work
with them
uh someone said uh i believe the
original question mentioned this but if
not sql what are you storing and what
does the interface to get that data look
like raw read as well key values uh yeah
so it's it's basically just custom coded
so um
because the server
so you know i mean i'm i'm an
architecture person i like working on
these kind of problems so like the last
thing i'm gonna do is have like a weird
like structured query language to do
stuff right like it's just going to be
like a nice little interface you can
just write raw c code that just works
right
so it's just custom whatever it needs
implemented it implements directly on
top of
that raw write system
and it's flexible right like it doesn't
i don't make like a procrustean sql like
bed for like all of my stuff to have to
sit on top of because you know
especially when you think about the fact
that like sql is not really meant
for many things it was really just meant
for like transaction processing right
and a lot of things you do on servers
aren't transaction processing some
things are like maybe the purchase
of
you know star code galaxy where you
retry click the buy button maybe that's
something that kind of looks like what
sql was designed for
but the rest of the stuff you know
anything else that there is really isn't
serving you back uh stuff to to um
when you try to read uh
stuff that's on the server like you're
trying to get like web server stuff to
you like it doesn't look like sql like
sql just wasn't designed for that and so
it's not a very it just isn't very
useful so the reason that people use
that kind of thing for for that nowadays
really just tends to be because it's
just what was there um and it's very
robust right because like transaction
processing was a very well studied
problem so you know you can go buy
something that probably won't just you
know light on fire and explode um but
it's usually not the right tool for the
job unless you're literally doing
you know like an atm machine sql server
or like a parts database where you have
to know exactly the number of screws
left in the inventory or whatever it's
just not really um
it's not really
that useful for a lot of things you do
uh have you looked into eb uh ebpf uh no
i have seen that mentioned and i even
looked at what it was
uh i thought i looked and said oh i
don't need to know about this is what
happened
uh but
maybe i'm wrong
uh
oh right this is the packet processing
thing
yes yes
uh no i have not looked into this i
don't think i care about it but i
haven't looked into it so i couldn't say
i did see it mentioned yes but no i
haven't i haven't
oh i okay windows is adding an iring
feature okay so i see the question is
why does it need
okay so so
i've read the sequel you're asking why
windows needs uh to add io ring if it
has iocp
um
i haven't looked at anything windows
related that looks like that so i don't
actually know
very much about
uh
what windows is planning to add for iou
ring
so i really couldn't comment what i will
say is
i o completion ports
are not solving the same problem
so i o completion ports the problem that
that is solving
is how you have multiple
threads
on the user side responding to
completion events from the system side
that is what iocp does
it is not designed for high bandwidth
outbound stuff
so it doesn't really have anything in
there designed to be a low latency
io
dispatch right
so at the very least you would think
that that would have to be there but the
other thing to think about
is that again it's still a call the
interface to iocp is a little clunky you
have to call get me all the completion
records and they copy them into your
buffer that's not really what you want
what you wanted was
a index you read without ever calling
the operating system and you see what it
is and that tells you where in your ring
buffer to read up through no operating
system involved right so again it's
about getting the calls out
this is how operating systems should
always have worked
uh
by about 1990 we should have started
moving towards operating systems where
this is all you did right you should
just write into memory and do it because
that's how old home computers used to
work right
um
you know what i'm saying
uh so really what you want is just
memory you right into that says here
this all the syscalls i want that's how
an operating system should always have
worked here's what this calls i want and
then i just look at an outbound queue to
see which one of those are done like
that's what you wanted that's what you
always wanted and it's what you had in a
certain extent to a certain extent um
although it was more interrupt it was
more like cause you know a single
processor so what are you gonna do
you're gonna interrupt and do it right
there but
what we should have moved to as we got
more cores was that and we didn't so you
know
somewhere in the 2000 to 2010 time frame
we really screwed up
uh and now it's just a question of like
trying to get back to normal
how do you organize the data
uh well that's yeah that's
a very very involved conversation
um
it would not make very much sense to
anyone other than me as i guess i would
say about how i organize the data
our overlap sends not going to be as
performant yeah i mean overlap sends
require
require you to actually call a function
right that function doesn't have to do a
syscall it could be a local call right
um but it's still to do something it's
not just rights
um you have to remember there's a big
difference between calling a function
and writing to memory calling a function
means you have to put a bunch of stuff
into registers
you have to issue the actual function
call
that function has to do some crap it has
to do the right you would have done
already and then it pops out the
compiler cannot optimize around it
because it doesn't know what that call
does it's a system call right it's not a
syscall but it is a call to a library
that the compiler can't see so it can't
do a bunch of optimizations if you're
talking about something where you just
know there's a flat memory
you know the format you need to write to
you can write code that blasts that in
there really quickly and the optimizer
can optimize straight over it everything
just works there's no call involved none
of that right
um and so you know again i don't know
the details of the windows one i can't
really say but i just want to point out
what the differences are there there's a
big difference between calling functions
to do stuff
um and just writing to memory
writing to memory is always a superior
option
john disagrees with me about this by the
way i don't know if he's still here
um
but but we had this argument once
and and he didn't believe me
so
uh
so you could you could argue with him
about that because i was like
you never call functions
to
prepare stuff to send to to the os like
that's not what you want what you want
is just you write flat memory
out
and the os picks it up
out of a queue right um
but john was like no you should have a
function that you call and then that
thing just does
the whatever the format stuff is that
needs to happen there right
um
and
i mean i guess one thing i would say is
it's probably the case that you could
find reasons why you would do one or the
other so it's not like there's a right
answer
but for me i always go the other way i'm
like no you just write everything right
[Music]
i would be totally fine yeah with an api
that it was just both ways yeah uh
because then it's like look if you can
if you can make
uh
performance gains by just going the
memory route then do so if you just
don't care
about that very much and you want to
make sure that you know it just does it
the way
you know it thinks it's best you just
call this function and it will do it for
you that totally seems fine too yeah
absolutely
i just always want the memory one
available because that's what i would
usually use
i think it also reduces dependency like
now i don't need that function right i
know that i can just make this flat
memory
it just it just i feel like it
simplifies my life a little bit as well
but
yeah
um
either way the idea here is just that
the ring structure is much more
efficient so even if you're going
through a function to do it
um
it's just going to be that ring on the
other side of that function anyway right
so that's might be why the windows
people are doing it maybe they already
have that ring is happening they're just
like let's just expose it right
do you have any tips in general on how
to go about reading and understanding
old large code repositories uh yes sir
uh get them building and step through in
the debugger
that's how i do it
um
let the debugger walk you through how
the code's working it's way easier uh in
my opinion do it that way
get a good debugger and and step through
it
yeah
john says i think the actual big
frontier in software that everyone
ignores is we have to make ways for
people to do things somewhat easily
without making it impossible to do the
efficient good version i totally agree
um
i mean this is part of the whole like
graphics api should probably just have
been something on github right
and then the vendors just like publish
the damn memory thing you write you know
because it's like we end up with this
weird in-between where it's like
you end up with something like
like really
messed up like vulcan
or
whatever where it's like it's like half
a raw memory api
but half a like
user api that's supposed to be doing
like we end up in these really weird
zones of like
that
or
the total ridiculous thing of like no
thought was given to the efficiency and
it's just like some it's like qt or
something you're just like oh my god
right
um
so yeah it's it's bad like like it would
be nice if we just said like we're
always gonna have a really clean
low-level thing where you just write to
memory
and you don't ever call anything
basically
and it works
but you have to be a pro to do it and
then if you want
go to this github
and get these libraries that will do
that for you and you call those
but they use the good thing underneath
that like anyone could use so you don't
have to use the library if it sucks or
whatever
it would be nice to get somewhere more
like that instead of like
sh they ship both things like we have
something that's supposed to be sort of
easy to use but also sort of performant
and it ends up being neither
right
um or they ship it and they know it's
not performant but there's some lie
about how it's gonna get performant and
it never does right
um
kind of like the c plus plus optimizer
like it's it's always like the optimizer
like it's gonna get better and then all
these problems are gonna go away and
then like it never does right so you
have these weird like vague promises
about why this will eventually be good
it's like well no like it probably won't
are you doing sort of check sums or
parity codes on disk rights
absolutely
um
so
when you write out data
uh you pretty much always want to hash
it right
i you really really want to know
if the data that you wrote out comes
back
the same
uh so so absolutely yeah i i stor i
start redundantly and i hash it so i
know uh when one of the redundant
versions is is bunk
yeah the ebpf stuff i don't know uh one
bit brain i just it just looked like i
was like i don't know if i care about
this because it just looked like
possibly a bad idea but you know i don't
know maybe it's great
it is true that in that space you often
have ridiculous stuff like
microcontrollers designed to do packet
filtering and they all have their own
like little like language thing and
whatever so like maybe it's good to just
standardize that i just i don't know
like the linux kernel is kind of going
off the deep end these days so i i'm
i don't know
i feel like they've piled too much
complexity in there and it's not a good
thing like that's not going to be good
down the line right
uh 3dfx glide is it was just open gel
really
3dfx slide is is not
it is just
pretty much just opengl it was it's
slightly different
but
but like if you could program opengl you
could just program glide right now like
you you would barely know the difference
i think
it was opengl back in the day though so
we're not talking about like modern over
gel we're talking about opengl where you
called like gl vertex for every vertex
kind of thing
that's what glide was like
yeah
all right
i should mention
so how are we doing here 8 27 got about
30 minutes left
so we could do some more questions
here in this programming anime
by the way i don't know if you guys got
to see it
i've got the book one comic book here it
looks pretty awesome
so if you're interested in checking out
the kickstarter for book 2
you should definitely do that i tried to
put a link at the bottom
i love the print job that they did on
this thing as i said before it's it's
really kind of awesome
if anyone out there is an artist who
wants to print a comic book you should
totally use this printer because they're
that good
uh it was really educational they just
have like such good like it just came
out so good and uh they even did the
spot uv on the front
just looks really good
anyway
uh yeah
check out our kickstarter if you don't
have questions
the link should be in the bottom but
i'll post it now
yeah let me see if i can get it to focus
uh here you go
i have the contrast turned way down so
you can't really see how vibrant the
colors are of course because that's just
i i don't like super vibrant webcams um
but it looks really good like they just
they're so good this printer was awesome
there's so many things that you don't
know about printing until you work with
a really good printer uh like to get all
of the stuff really crisp and the colors
just right
um
they are so good it looks way better
than most of the stuff we've got from
other places like we've got comics on
the shelf here you know
and a lot of them just don't look that
good like the colors are kind of not
that great and the end like there's you
know there's the edging is not perfect
or it's a little bit blurry or whatever
right
um and this place was just awesome they
were so good they're here in seattle too
they're like local it was awesome
but anyway yeah
if you don't have book one the
kickstarter for book two you can get
book one too so check it out if you want
a good if you want a good feline space
opera
uh
you know
you you would be hard pressed to find
a better comic than me on the infinite
so we need some more questions here
besides all the horrors you've seen in
regards to getting desired hardware
performance in your server work what
have you found
on this endeavor that's been pretty
interesting
i mean it really depends on what you're
talking about
um
i guess i would say uh programming wise
i
think i was pleasantly surprised by wasm
um
the webassembly spec
it's not
what i would want
exactly
but it was
they it's like fairly simple like they
were like look we're just gonna have
a few instructions they fit on like one
simple html page like here's all the
instructions that they're gonna be we're
just gonna compile c to it there's no
like all the m script and stuff and all
that stuff is garbage and stupid but the
actual just hey i can put together a
little assembly language and i can send
it to the browser and it works
i was pleasantly surprised
because everything else i've ever seen
from the w3c is like the exact opposite
of that right
it's like
thousands of pages to implement a simple
layout language that doesn't really work
right like css or something right
so like i feel like the people who did
wasm
manage to avoid
the thing that all the other w3c specs
do which is end up with
gigantic piles of api
and then they still don't freaking work
right
um the wasm stuff like kind of works
like it kind of works and it's kind of
simple it's it's by far the best thing
i've seen out of the w3c
i wish the mem they had there's a
there's a little bit
so they haven't really figured out good
answers to like how you get memory
working exactly right
and that's unfortunate
the single 32-bit address space thing
that they do
has
it really limits
what the code can do in terms of
efficiency like that's that's not good
i would really have liked it if they
would have tackled that head-on and
appreciated the importance of the mmu
okay
but
that said i'm just talking i'm not
talking about this compared to the
ultimate thing i'm just talking about
this compared to everything else that is
in your browser
this was surprisingly good to me right
because everything else is in the
browser is nowhere near usable
right it's not like with wasm i'd be
like okay here's the here's the things i
think maybe we could do better here
right
the the thing you could do better with
css is throw it away right right it's
complete garbage there's nothing good
about it i have nothing positive to say
right so if you take a look at the
difference between something like css
and something like wasm i just think
they deserve some credit for
not doing the thing that they always do
so the people who did wasm i i really
like the fact that they stayed out of
some of these disasters
disastrous traps that all the other web
tech has gone down and so that was
pleasant
it was really freaking easy
to get my wasm stuff working
as a thing to ship for our client code
the compatibility may not be fabulous
yet so you know
we'll see about that
but i'm just saying it's off to a much
better start right it's off to a much
better start than these other things
where you just look at them and you just
go like oh my god you know
what are your thoughts on cpu side
channel attack mitigation seriously
affected the performance of memory
mapped files and io in general do you
think the api should have a way to opt
out of that i've seen 2 to 8x
performance loss in my code because of
this
wow really 2 to 8x performance
that's crazy um
so i guess what i would say is i don't
have a lot of experience with it
um thus far i have not had the uh
i've never had the experience of finding
out that the reason that my code was
running slow is because of a side
channel attack mitigation
um
so i'm i
have nothing to add
i do think that being able to opt out of
them would be a good idea uh the reason
for that is just that
if you're running a dedicated server
there is no side channel attack right
um nobody is running code on your
machine just you so no one can do
spectre no one can do meltdown
no one can do row hammer right
and the only way anyone's ever going to
mount an attack like that
would be if they found some really good
exploits about how to get your code to
issue the attack on itself
and i just don't see that being very
plausible there are plenty of side
channel attacks that work on servers but
they're usually side channel attacks
like
leakage about how much time something
takes right
they don't tend to be
uh
to the like time like actual wall clock
time um they don't tend to be down to
the kind of like cycle accurate sort of
stuff you probably have to do
um for side channel stuff and also they
wouldn't be like
nothing is going through a ring
transition so that like i'm not sure
where the side channel part comes in
right so you pretty much have to defend
against those things already when you're
writing a server uh because of the user
space pro
attack as well that happens there so i'm
pretty sure it's just not an issue so it
would be nice to disable some of those
because they're really just not an issue
for servers
um that aren't running other people's
code you know
but you know who knows i don't know
what's the thing you're most excited for
or proud of you've been working on in
the last 12 months like the most
positive thing
[Music]
i guess there's two things i don't know
i'll say two things
so one thing
is
the
the distribution algorithm
like like how the architecture is for
our server thing we're deploying for how
it scales right so how you
add more machines to it
um it's also thing i'm most terrified
about right
so
so like
i think i did a good architecture for
that solution it's a very hard problem
it's the hardest problem you face in
server design is is how do you
run many servers without the cost of
running many servers
without the communication between the
servers like you know limiting a lot of
the gain you get or creating bugs or
creating slow downs that sort of thing
i'm excited for how i solve that problem
i'm also terrified because
the only way you ever know if that works
is when you get like eight machines deep
because people actually liked your
service and you had to add more and then
you find out it didn't doesn't work
right
um
so you know uh i've been trying to war
game it out as best i can but there's
nothing that's the same as actually
deploying right i mean there's nothing
that's the same as
you can try to simulate all you want but
nothing is the same exactly the same as
when you actually
deploy so
you know
uh so there's that the other thing uh is
is stupid but i actually am excited
about it which is the star code galaxy
the text version
there there's like a
there's like a thing
at the beginning of star code galaxy the
first things you do is like a text
like it looks like a roguelike kind of
thing you know like like you know the
old school with the ascii text thing
and
i i did some stuff in that in the code
base there that i thought was pretty fun
like you know see you'll see when it
comes out
it's stupid it's not
it wasn't hard or interesting really but
it was just like oh it was kind of fun
you know so there's there are some fun
stuff in there because you know
i never got a chance to do uh uh one of
those ascii
dungeon things so you know it was
sprint entertaining
yeah lucid frost five to ten percent
sounds more like what i would have
expected that the two to eight times
just doesn't sound right are you sure
that's what it was it just sounds wrong
to me now i don't know because i don't
you know like i said i've never really
hunted down a thing like that so i'm i'm
not prepared to say that you're wrong
because you may be right you know it's
just 2 day 8x just doesn't sound
plausible for a side channel mitigation
is the small instruction set for wasm
libel to be enough x86 is a big isa and
i imagine much of the of that variety
provides value
so
i think what i would say is
obviously you're you're not wrong
uh
you're definitely going to lose some
things because you go to a smaller
instruction set you and x86 gets some
power out of being this big old beefy
nightmare instruction set that's kind of
one of the things that it gets power
from like having memory operands for
everything
and having these gigantic long
instructions to do 50 million things or
whatever
no question right
but you have to remember
not everything
is about taking advantage of maximum
performance there are
and
one of the things so it's it's important
distinguish
when i get really angry at web
technology it's not
because it's slow per se
meaning i'm usually not angry that web
stuff
is slow and that's the only thing it's
just i'm just angry about the slowness
what i'm angry about is it fails on all
fronts it's slow
it's buggy it doesn't actually work
right it's ugly it's unreliable right
so it's kind of like they had a problem
to solve many problems they could solve
and they solved none of them right
the thing i like about wasm is
it seems to actually solve a little bit
of a problem
is it going to be the fastest way to run
x86 code absolutely not
is it going to be relatively fast yes
right
it's relatively fast
it supports threads
it supports arbitrary addressing it just
can't do the full 64-bit mmu stuff which
is a bummer like i said
it has 128-bit cmd support not all the
instructions but a lot of them
right
and it's very simple the instruction set
fits on a couple pages you can read it
you can understand it you can look at a
disassembly
and you can see what it's doing
that's a success to me
is it
is it the best on any particular access
no is it a reasonable solution to a real
problem that i feel like i can use to
deploy something that will actually work
and that i won't hate and that is fast
enough to be usable and reasonably have
a good user experience yes i do think so
i think it might be we'll see
i think it might be
and that to me is a success coming from
the w3c that is a success because most
of their things accomplish none of those
they aren't fast enough to be usable
they aren't reliable enough to be usable
they aren't
precise or rigorous enough to be usable
right
so if wasm had tried to have like 8 000
instructions i think that might have
been a mistake
right
yes you could have gotten some more
performance out of it by having a richer
target but you lose something you lose
the simplicity
um and it makes the the transpiler
harder the thing that actually goes and
turns that into machine code that's in
all the browsers it makes that easier to
screw up it makes it more likely to
introduce slowness because the
transpiler sucked right so you have to
remember there's multiple things they
had to optimize for
when doing something like wasm and
normally that is the kind of thing that
w3c just completely fails at and in my
opinion they did not completely fail
this time
wasm is not the horror show that their
other specs are
is it as good as it could be no but
nothing is
do i hope it gets a little bit better
over time yes but is it an epic disaster
no
and that is something
however small to celebrate when it comes
to the web
right
i'm young dev working as a front-end
developer and i feel like there's not
much i can do to apply handmade
principles to regular js coding
day-to-day do you have any tips for
doing that when you have to work with
the standard front-end html css js stack
um
i mean yes and no what i will say is
that uh obviously if you can use wasm
well there you go you can compile c
right in there and run it inside your js
just fine
so that's one way to pull the escape
hatch
but
one thing i would say is
html css
you can program that more low level
right html css js you can program that
more low level
you can
uh instead of like using 20 000
frameworks and like calling like react
and all this stuff from js you can
actually think about like how do i write
very straightforward
simple javascript code that does what i
actually needed to do more efficiently
and and you will see the benefits when
you don't have to download this giant
react.js
like or you know framework
that just dumps all this crap in there
your pages load faster they run faster
they're less buggy because you can see
you know when you wrote it you wrote
exactly what needed to happen so you can
apply handmade principles to anything
it's just don't use more than you have
to it's really it's just being you know
frugal is what it is so it doesn't
matter what you're programming in you
can still cut down on the crap so if you
have to work on js yeah it's an annoying
language it sucks i mean it does
javascript is a terrible language
uh but hey i mean
you can still not use all these bloated
libraries and you can write your own
little custom stuff that's cleaner more
straightforward and more likely to work
and it will have uh benefits of being
faster because your page load times will
go down and your interpreter times will
go down right
that's cool that you can turn
mitigations off by putting mitigations
off in a set s config grub okay that's
cool
that's cool yeah
interesting mitigations for 288x on a
pneuma system with mcdram caches
on a regular desktop x8664 it's about 15
percent that's such a big difference
right
wow
yeah i've never had that experience
obviously
oh freak cs yes uh so starco galaxy is
coming um
when i get the
uh
this server system deployed
uh then i will be working on getting it
out
runs on top of it basically
uh so the the the coding course is star
code galaxy i sent out a mail today in
fact those of you who are on the circle
galaxy mailing list should have gotten a
mail today hopefully everyone got it
startedgalaxy.com has a little signup
sheet i sent out a mail um and it talks
a little bit about
what we're what we're working on and
what's still to go
so
in ref term you annotated the headers
and seem to have split things up to make
things like the glyph table use like a
library would you say that's a good
example of an api you made
um yeah i mean that
you know that was a weekend project so i
don't really want to say it's a good
example of an api but that's just how
you ship code sanely in my opinion right
like if you go look at that glyph table
uh it's pretty easy to use right i made
sure that the things you call make sense
that anyone could grab it and drop it in
and they'd be unlikely to screw it up
right could i have done more though
definitely sure
um but if you look at that glyph table
you can see that you know i took a
little time to make sure it was easy to
drop it in and you know it's not
probably not the best api i could think
of like if i went and thought hard about
it
but it's a usable api and more
importantly it's an api that comes out
of having written the thing that needs
to use the api so i know that the api
fits into place properly uh to a
terminal right which is which is also
one of the that's the most important
thing in an api right is that the shape
of the api
is useful to the people who want to use
it and they don't have to do all this
code to work around the fact that the
api doesn't naturally call
the way that you
need it to for the thing the problem
it's supposed to solve you know
in the printing creation of meow the
infinite did you have to write and code
uh
so i'm not exactly sure what that
question is but actually i did write
some code
for
meow the infinite uh
so let me show you book two
so the the kickstarter that i posted
um
the kickstarter that we're running right
now which please check out if you get a
chance it's got a cool trailer and
everything
um i'll post it here
um
i don't know if i did any code
that was would be used in book two but
in book one and some of you know about
this because i posted it on my blog in
book one there's this character that's
like this creepy autonomous
automaton cat let me show you
so there's this there's this like
ancient um
mechanical marvel
right it's right there it's called the
prime puss
uh and you can go to have an audience
with it
right that's one of the things that you
can uh that you can do in this world is
like people go to have an audience you
bite
let me just show you
sorry about spoilers if you don't want
spoilers plug your ears for a second um
but you would have if you would have
already bought the book
so
you go you go to this place called comet
city and you buy one of these little
tickets
right
um and you can have an audience with the
prime puss
and it's it's this this thing here right
and if you look at the text
there was no real way to do that in like
photoshop um and anna would have had to
have like done all that by hand and just
didn't
it didn't make any sense because if you
look i'll try to zoom it in even closer
if i can
if you look it's like all jittery and
the size
like i mean at the size the the offset
uh bait for the baseline is different
um and stuff like that
right
um so if you look at something like that
uh
it's like it takes too long to create by
hand so what i did is i wrote like a
photoshop script that does that for you
automatically
it didn't take very long but photoscrap
photoshop has like a little like
really crappy like javascript thing in
it um
so so you can do stuff like that like
you can go take the text and like assign
random randomized baseline so there's
like a little thing that you could plug
in some numbers to
and it would just like randomize the
text and that made it a lot easier so
your email went to spam but i found it
thanks yeah gosh i don't know what to do
about that we tried to send out so
we used to send out a really bare bones
email um i don't know those of you have
been on the molly rocket wailing list
for potentially years because we've it's
been around forever like we send out
project updates occasionally to it we've
been doing that forever
um i don't know that we used to have
much of a problem with spam
uh but like somehow we ended up we now
get filed to spam a lot we tried this
time
to have ours not go to spam by making we
we made a an email template that's a lot
more like
um what you normally get for advertising
emails or whatever
but apparently it's the webspam
so i don't i don't know what to do about
that uh i mean i do know to do it long
term it's just stop doing email
um
we
we need to like move past it uh
we need it we need a new infrastructure
for the web where people who sign up for
things get them
right
spam was a stupid idea anyway
you could have just had it so that
people said which addresses they wanted
to receive stuff from and then they get
them right
you shouldn't even have to sign up for a
mailing list you should just put that as
a thing in your email that's like rss
basically right
so
yeah i don't know what to do i do not
know why gmail puts us in spam
probably because i complain about how
much google sucks all the time
but i don't know if anyone knows how to
how to d how to stop getting us spam
like that it's really annoying it's it's
it's almost like it's one of those
things where i wish you could just like
sue them right it's like look people
signed up for this
your responsibility was to deliver this
to them you're calling it spam it's like
what the heck dude like you have to fix
this but they never will right
what email address was it sent from it's
sent via spark post
so so it's it's it's sent via like a
commercial
email provider right
um
and it has it has proper
uh
you know like if you go look at our dns
on mollyrocket.com it has the proper
like authentication stuff
for proving that this is like a legit
legit mail one of those spv spf whatever
the stupid
thing is right
um
and it's it's set up to be correct and
the weird part too is it never goes to
spam for us so we don't get to know
that that happened
um
[Music]
so like it's just it sucks it's really
sucks i don't know how to say it other
than that it sucks and i don't know how
google decides these things because of
course they won't tell you
uh and i just don't understand like i
don't know what you do about it
since google is an advertising company
they probably want to to just like file
everything to spam so you have to pay
them to advertise
um
it's not great
uh but yeah it's really annoying because
we'd like to be able to communicate with
the customers who literally told us they
want us to send them an email and it
really sucks that we can't do that you
know
but
but that's the way it is
so
yeah i don't know
yeah it comes from mollymail
mollyrocket.com yeah did anyone get it
who and it wasn't sent to spam
i'm curious if it
so weird so like it thinks it's spam for
some people and it doesn't think it's
spam for other people
so i'm guessing that it's like depending
on what things you've marked spam before
like if you've marked things like that
as spam or maybe you marked ours as spam
before because you didn't like it i
don't know
i really don't know because it's weird
that multiple people
some people get it and it's spam and
some people don't
um and like i'm on gmail it doesn't go
to my spam
right
um
and like somebody posted that they have
gmail and it went to their spam
why right i i just don't know you'd
think gmail either thinks it's spam or
doesn't think it's spam
uh but that's obviously not the case so
you know how is it spam for one person
and not spam for another that
right
uh so i don't know how to fix that and
maybe we need to switch to a different
provider
um
you know maybe we should just switch to
a different provider i don't know
uh
but i'd really like to get it fixed
because it's very hard for us to
communicate with people without it right
um
yeah the sundial yeah
the sundial ones go through who the who
knows
uh no there's not going to be any
capacity for the scg course it's it's
just it's it's own thing that you can
just buy
so
the the weird thing imc bass or the
weird thing that i can't figure out
right though is because if it was a
question of who it came from
then why aren't they all going to spam
like why do some people it doesn't go to
spam
for gmail and why do other people it
does so it just seems buggy
because if they marked ips as having
sent spam they should all go
like nobody should get it in their inbox
right
how is it possible that some people get
it and some people don't it's really
frustrating
um
and and i just do not know so what we
might try to do
is like switch to different provider
um
and see if that has any better luck
uh but i don't know what else to do like
i don't know who else i don't know what
to do i don't think we could improve
matters by serving the spam ourselves
right
um
right so if we try to send the email
i'm assuming that'd be even less likely
to go through because then it's not
coming from a known location at least
gmail knows that spark post is the back
end for lots of people's mailing lists
so they should be expecting to get it
and i don't know what's going on
um
there but like at least it's not
they know it's not a dedicated spam
house
but i really just don't know
um
but it's but it's really it's really
nasty
i may have to just switch away like like
here's a question for those of you out
there who might know
um
who should you send your
mailing list through
you know
like what's the way to send a marketing
email
because i honestly don't know
you want to use a commercial esp like
mailchimp or iterable or whoever but you
have to warm your ips properly you have
to maintain the quality of your list
over time like if you send stuff out and
get poor open rates you'll be penalized
but we don't include any tracking
there are no open rates
like what does that even mean
like like we don't have click tracking
in our
in our emails
so so i don't really know
it's really troublesome though this is a
disaster like we used to have no problem
like we used to send out the mailing
list every week
for a while and we had no problems fast
forward a few years and now we just
can't seem to i don't know it's really
really it really bothers me
um
[Music]
so i don't know
yeah nxsy uh well neil
um
i was wondering that
actually like i was wondering if our
mail looks too much like spam because it
doesn't have a bunch of tracking crap
in it or something
um which is the if that were actually
true that'd be like the most offensive
thing that's
could possibly happen you try to send an
email to your customers
that doesn't try to
screw them and capture all their
information
and you get penalized
i don't know man it's very frustrating
um
and
i just don't understand
but
yeah email is garbage i'm not sure what
else you use i mean i can't post anybody
on twitter nobody reads my twitter
right
um
but it's really bad like it's a massive
problem
um
and like people should just be getting
sued
like like i feel like someone should
just class action google about this it's
just it's unacceptable right
it's it's really not cool
well our mailing list has like 9 000
people on it
and like
when we send out a mail lots of people
read it
if i post a tweet about something like
one of our projects it gets like seven
likes
right nobody cares
um
so there's a pretty big difference and
that's with
most of it going to spam even so like
the mailing list seems to work better
even to this day even with all the spam
but i just don't it's really very it
makes me very unhappy i do
uh think there's possibilities for
replacing in the future with better
things
um
and so we'll see
it definitely enrages me to the point
where it's like you know
uh since we're distributing a server
architecture it has stuff baked in there
now so that you can get updates from us
directly without going through gmail
because of this exact reason it
definitely does just like increase my
level of rage
that just makes me want to freaking
destroy
places like gmail
for being so freaking terrible and not
caring about their customers even the
slightest bit
it sounds like uh hotmail outlook i
think they're the same right it sounds
like somehow they just didn't accept it
this is terrible it makes me so
depressed
this is their only job
right
it's so ridiculous it's just so freaking
terrible
these companies need to go away they
can't do anything
google is like one of the most
incompetent piles of failure
i have ever seen for a trillion dollar
company it's absolutely insane
it's just ridiculous how hard is it to
send text back and forth the answer is
infinitely hard if you're google
or microsoft
as it turns out
yeah mailjet.com what is that
i feel like mail jet so they're okay but
they weren't originally mail jet wasn't
originally an smtp server right that's a
new thing i think
but i i think i'm gonna have to switch
away from spark post because it just
doesn't seem like we get any good
delivery but maybe that's our fault i
don't know like i said you can't tell
because one of the problems with the
quote unquote spam filtering is that
they hide everything from you because
they want to make sure that spammers
can't work their way around it the
problem is that means legitimate people
can't work their way around it like
they don't solve the problem by doing
what they do
they're not solving the problem
you know um
with the header validation i'm seeing
spf pass and dkm pass but none from
dmarc
send grid is the biggest
what's dmarc so maybe we have to add
that maybe that was something that got
added since then
that i don't know about
so maybe i'll look into that after but i
just really want to get this
straightened out because it's very
depressing and i guess the the right
thing to look at it is like i just have
to build a better way for us to
communicate with our customers which
i'll now be able to do which is nice
right
um because we'll actually have a server
infrastructure up so i can start to do
things to replace these ridiculously
crappy services
that suck and can't even do basic things
like send text back and forth but it's
like that's you know
i need a way to
bootstrap that process and you know i
need to somehow
right i need to be able to communicate
with our customers to the up until the
point where you can actually create a
better conduit
um
so i don't know
but i'll look at that dmarc thing
because maybe that is part of it i don't
know like that was not something you
could do back when we set this up
originally so maybe we need to set that
up
uh
right
uh and we'll see
i'll have to look
i can log into the spark post thing now
and see see if it's see if it's there
um
so i don't see anything about dmarc here
so maybe i have to i'll have to go read
up about it i don't see anything about
that like it does
you know it's got the stuff about like
adding cname records in the text records
but i don't see anything
uh on here about about dmarc
have to go read up on what that is
send grid huh
i'll look at them as well because we're
just we're not having any luck with
spark posts so i'll have to look and see
if i can find another option
thanks for the tips though because i
really want to get this straightened out
at least to a certain degree so
so we'll see
all right folks so i think we're
basically at time here i said it was
till nine and it's a nine
thanks for hanging out
hopefully some of those
question answers were useful
and thanks for the suggestions about the
the spam stuff because i yeah i need
something to try we can't really keep
going the way we're going because we
can't even send mail to our own mailing
list which is kind of ridiculous
um
so
i would like to at least try to get it a
little bit better
uh
and you know so i can try the send grid
stuff and i'll just i'll just try it
right i'll just try
and see because if we get it if it's
better it's better
um
but at least it gives me something
proactive i can do whereas right now you
know there's nothing proactive for me to
do which is a frustrating feeling
i have my own mail server but
thunderbird put it in spam there you go
thanks thunderbird
all of this stuff has to get rebuilt
guys it has to i mean
think about how simple this problem is
if instead of signing up for a mailing
list you just put into your email
program the email address that you were
trying to subscribe to
none of this would be a problem
right
because it would be pull instead of push
so like rss is the right solution to
this problem or something similar right
um
and they were just like now
like that's just no
we can't do that we have to do this
ridiculous stupid idea
yeah i mean rss wasn't perfect
i wouldn't use that term but at least
it's reliable like you know that anybody
who wanted to get your mailing list will
get it if rss was still a thing now
nobody uses rss nobody even knows what
it is so you can't really operate a
mailing list using rss because you would
have like six customers the six people
who still remember how to use rss right
but that was the correct answer you
should have just had a thing in you on
your inbox just said add feed and they
would just show up as males
right i mean how hard would that have
been
but no
anyway thank you very much everyone for
joining me uh
yeah
it was it was fun answering questions it
was not so fun talking about the spam
thing because that always upsets me
every time i find that out
um
but
semi-damn idea you could set up a
newsletter on sub stack
so that's not a dumb idea i mean i would
be fine setting up a newsletter on
substance
uh
so you know that's not a dumb idea
you said it you called it a dumb idea
well you called it a semi-dumb idea so i
think you knew there was at least some
smartness in there you knew it
because then it's like okay it's coming
from sub sac if they stop start
sending sub stack to spam
then like
people who paid for this newsletter are
not going to get it or whatever right
because like there's a bunch of people
who charge for their newsletters on
substance
so in theory if you start a newsletter
on subsect that's not
paid it's just free
which as far as i know you can do
um
you might be able to just kind of like
ride those coattails right it's like
yeah we're just using this as our
company's mailing list unfortunately i
can't import our existing mailing list
to substack
um
[Music]
at least i don't think you can
but you know i could try to communicate
with our customers that if they are
having trouble getting delivery
of our email because the people at
google
learn to program
from a toll-free number they got in a
cracker jack box
um you know maybe that's like just
another option i just like
you know i send the newsletter out via
sendgrid or something and maybe get some
people maybe it doesn't and then if
people have been having trouble getting
the newsletter
delivered to them
they can they know that they can go to
sub stack and subscribe there and have a
better chance of getting it
not a bad idea
uh i i could see giving that a shot i
mean what do i have to lose right i copy
the email over to substack
right
um
so like that seems pretty good
that seems actually pretty good
thank you for that semi-dumb idea which
i'm gonna have to say is not semi-dumb
at all
so
i'm gonna go think about that that's
what i'm going to do as soon as i
close this stream
so thank you that was great that's a
very good idea
i'm sorry it's a semi-dumb idea
according to you but according to me
it's actually a pretty good idea
all right everybody
thanks for joining me
um
we'll have some more stuff to talk about
i think during the uh during the
infinite kickstarter we're trying to do
a couple other things for promotional
stuff for sure but
for the most part
uh it'll be a normal weekend i'll be
back here on sunday to do handmade
heroes so they'll be that as well
i'm gonna go see if i can figure out
about that subsection because that's
actually a pretty good idea that's a way
that they can't really
screw you quite quite the way that they
currently are because now you've got a
lot more angry people if they start to
block that email address so that's not a
bad idea i might give that a shot thanks
for the suggestions
i will report back if i if i try that
maybe on sunday um during handmade here
i'll i'll
i'll give a little postmortem on how
that went if i give it a shot all right
thanks everybody
um i will uh i'll see you guys on sunday
until then
have fun programming and i'll see you on
the internet take it easy everybody