hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here the show where we normally code a
complete game live on stream but during
the pre stream today I kind of got riled
up as I sometimes do talking about how
bad modern hardware and offering systems
have gotten mm hmm and it reminded me
that I did have a lecture on this topic
that I never recorded and so I kind of
wanted to just go ahead and record it
now I do apologize because normally what
you would do with a lecture and what I
do do with a lecture is rehearse it
first
unlike handmade Hiro which is just
seat-of-the-pants by design and by
intent normally a lecture is much better
if rehearsed and I did rehearse it when
I gave it the first time but I think it
was something like six years ago and so
I suspect that this will be pretty rough
but I wanted to get it out there just so
I could have the material for reference
anyway this lecture is called the 30
million line problem and it is a lecture
about the dangers of how we have let
hardware and operating system design
kind of run away and become untenable
and without further ado let me just jump
right into it it's not a particularly
long lecture I think it's meant to take
about 30 minutes all right so one thing
that we can all appreciate and that I
think is always the starting point for
discussions like this is just an
appreciation of the extreme difference
between the kinds of hardware that I had
when I was a child or whenever you were
a child or the hardware you can first
remember and the hardware you get to
program today and the fact that says
2015 on there I'm guessing that's when I
first gave this lecture so three years
ago I guess yeah this would be even
higher today I and so when I look at
these two things that 2015 there that's
the machine that we were programming
handmade hero on and that machine was
actually a 2010 machine so the machine
was actually five years old at the time
that I'm talking about it and that's
what I was programming on 2015 nowadays
on hammer here we actually updated to a
machine that's way way more powerful
than
this machine so it's worth pointing that
out but if you look at these two in 1990
my processor was 25 megahertz it was it
was an Amiga computer as 25 megahertz
and now in 2015 not only are the speeds
you know a hundred times faster that 2.8
get your Hertz right but they're also
more of them so you don't just have one
processor anymore for a CPU you've got
four of them effectively in that
particular machine and each one of
them's actually also has four wide ALU
units right it can actually issue for
time now the Ale units are eight
sometimes 16 wide and you have hyper
threads as well and the core counts are
going up above four it's just there's an
orgy of hardware in there obviously the
graphics was way simpler back then 320
by 512 by 5 will now we're up to you
know this at a minimum and that was like
I said on a much crappier machine than
the one now so 4k displays are common
now as well the number six
and the number eight are very close for
memory only the power of a thousand has
changed it's gone from megabytes to
gigabytes right and not only do we have
more memory by a factor of a thousand
but we even have that memory on two
different processors so you have that
much memory on your main processor and
on your graphics processor in 1990 it
was shared between the two and of course
hard drives are absurd I don't even want
to go into those right so when you look
at that picture really all you can say
is at least from the the strictly
density side of things hardware
developers have delivered fantastic
gains in the past 25 years now 28 years
however the software that we use is way
worse than it's ever been the experience
using the computer in 2015 or today 2018
compared to what it was like using it
back when on the computer that's
furniture before the computers using
before was a very
serene and pleasant experience the only
time it really ever became frustrating
was it didn't the CPU didn't even have
memory protection so when you were
programming an application you might
introduce a bug that would overwrite
some memory and cause your operating
system to crash right and that was
really unfortunate and nowadays we are
fortunate to have CPUs that have virtual
memory protection and they don't have to
have this problem anymore so that's
great so we fixed one problem pretty
much the only problem that we used to
have back then and in exchange for that
one fix unfortunately are for whatever
reasons our software has become almost
unusable and it's unusable in many many
many different ways these are just some
screenshots of things I see every day
basically these are not uncommon they're
my common experience using computer I
the twitter is over capacity fail whale
I don't think shows up very much for me
and the desktop anymore but amusingly I
now for the first time have an Android
phone I didn't have a smartphone for a
long time I got a an Android smartphone
recently and it cannot ever load Twitter
from a URL if you go to twitter.com
it just says Twitter is taking too long
to load in a little message and no
matter how many times your refresher
it'll never load you have to like go
back to the title bar Andry force it to
reload the page and then sometimes it
will work right so even that one that
maybe sort of got fixed really didn't
because now we just got the other ones
so anyway when you use software today
what you generally see is a huge array
of viruses and software instability and
updates that happen when you don't want
them to and message boxes that pop up
that you can't control and your
operating system rebooting and losing
work and doing all these are sort of
things even the hardware now has failure
design into it you try to plug in to
things to play video from your computer
to your television and it turns out you
can't play it because some weird like
HDCP thing has decided that even though
you are using a legitimately purchased
blu-ray
legitimately purchased television it
just doesn't work right I and this is
really frustrating it causes such a
loathesome experience with a personal
computer that you just want to throw the
thing out the window a lot of times if
you do anything at all with your
computer that isn't just checking
Facebook once in a while and even that
can become kind of frustrating hmm I and
sometimes these things aren't just
frustrating they're actually really
detrimental right and there was some
kind of absolutely ridiculous thing in
the news back on the day or close to the
day when I was doing this lecture
originally you could go find new ones
today they happen all the time but this
was a kind of funny one headline that
you read and it's like something was
going on where you were needed a
computer to actually work in order to do
something for a real-world consequence
and of course windows update or
something decided it needed to update
and they couldn't use the computer and
then they ended up in a situation that
actually cost them something significant
and you read all these funny stories but
there it's not funny right like that's
just not that funny when you actually
think about how bad computing has failed
when ostensibly it's come so far the
hardware that they were using for
whatever this situation is was so much
better than the one that I was talking
about in 1990 yet this never would have
happened in 1990 right and so one of the
things that I think we need to step back
and think about is why is software so
much less reliable and so much more
unpleasant to use today than it was it
should be much more pleasant to use
today the hardware is so much better and
it is so much easier to get reasonable
performance out of it that you would
think that he's apt to assume but
remember these are applications that are
oftentimes very close to identical to
the ones we were using a word processor
on say an Amiga computer from 1990 and a
word processor of today the performance
it's aren't that different actually
right and yet the one running on the
thousands and thousands of times faster
machine is somehow still as slow or
slower when you're actually trying to
type things into it and it's laying out
the text you know and so we have to
think about why if it should be so much
easier to make software today why is it
actually seem to often times not get any
better although we do add features over
time certainly the experience doesn't
seem to get much better and also all of
these other aspects of the experience
that are horrible all of sudden start
coming in why are there all these long
load times and spinning progress bars
that never seem to complete and crashes
and all these other things why are all
of these things seem to be more rampant
rather than less when we should be
having an easier time right with with
making the software and more of our
focus it should be easy to have more of
our focus spent on reliability and all
the sort of stuff because we're doing
fundamentally hopefully less work to
make a reasonably performant experience
for the end-user that's what we would
think well I would posit that the reason
is actually very easy to understand I
think the reason is simply that since
things are no longer coded from scratch
from start what we end up doing is we
just pile code on top of code on top of
code right and so any thing that might
have been problematic or wrong about any
underlying layer and that could interact
with any other layer that we put on top
of it they all just keep multiplying
together to multiply out in almost an
exponential fashion our failure rates
and our performance problems right and
what I've done here is I've constructed
a graph of operating system just the
operating system nothing else over time
in what you can see here is that the
operating system back in 1991 this is
Linux I believe was so small that on
this graph that
the current size of Linux on the far
right end and mind you this was 2015
size of Linux actually so we haven't
even got no 2018 it's still going up
right the original size of the Linux
operating system when it debuted was so
small that it looks like it doesn't
exist on this chart it's - well b0 right
yet the size of the same operating
system today which granted does a lot
more things so I'm not saying it's
equivalent I'm just saying what you
actually need if you're just wondering
on the link system the kernel has now
gotten up to over 18 million lines and
now again I want to say this is just
absolute when I say just yapping system
I don't even mean X Windows I don't mean
the good news standard library I mean
like just the kernel source tree which
admittedly includes some like
documentation and things like this but
this is looking at the lines of code in
just the kernel okay so now let's ask
the question because that's pretty bad
right let's ask the question on this
machine how many lines of code would it
take to read a text file right all I
want to do is I want to read in a text
file that's an operation that we might
do today right and if you think about
the way that a modern person reads a
text file they're in a web browser and
the web browser goes to a URL it
downloads a text file and displays it
onto the screen how many lines of code
must be functioning properly and
performant Lee in order for that
experience to work reliably and well the
answer is I don't know but it's not less
than 56 million I'm not kidding this is
basically what it looks like right I
picked
random possible way that a website might
commonly work such as a lamp stack right
running WordPress but you could
substitute those out with anything else
you wanted they are not particularly
high contributors right
so let's take a look at what I'm talking
about here first of all you need a web
browser
I picked chrome but all of them are
fairly large just to run that web
browser is 16 million lines of code that
have to be functioning properly in order
for your browser to work well and not
crash right underneath that you needed
an operating system and that operating
system I picked Linux that's at least 17
million lines of code again right that
had to be working properly now do all of
those lines either work probably no
right because obviously there are code
paths that will not be lit up when you
do this but since you don't know which
ones those are if you were to ask a
person to go verify that this would work
okay that is what they be staring at
they'll know which ones are going to be
hit by this path right they have to
start to understand 17 million lines of
codes layout roughly before they would
even know what section of focus our
attention on if they want to improve the
performance or stability thereof right
so you need at least Chrome and Linux I
didn't even count X Windows in here but
you probably need at least some
substrate the most minimal version of
this probably includes more that's why
it's a minimum bound that I've said
right so then on top of that I said well
there's probably something like open up
wrt running right you need your router
the thing that's actually taking the
packets off of your ethernet card and
getting them out to the internet right
that's gonna be another 1.5 million
lines of code or something like that
somewhere in there there's probably a
Cisco router probably be multiple of
them who knows probably other routers I
don't know the backbone structure but
depending on the hops between you and
the other side of where you're reading
the text file that code is probably many
many millions of lines of code so we're
understanding this by a huge amount
because all of the OS is of all of the
routers
their firmware not counted here
similarly I didn't count the firmware of
the machine that the Chrome and Linux
setup was running on so then it gets to
the other side okay and let's say the
other side isn't running Linux let's say
maybe it's running FreeBSD right because
that's got a lower line count so the
lowest line count it might be running on
the other side would be something like
13 million but that might be more like
17 million if it's running Linux or it
may be if let's say it's running
something like Windows or some other
custom thing and AWS on the other side
might be on this side right
who knows those are many many millions
of lines more but so somewhere in the
order of 10 to 20 millions of lines at
least is coming into play there then
you've got all of the lines of code
necessary to run the thing that actually
served you it to you and oftentimes
that's something like a lamp stack
Apache PHP WordPress my sequel for
example that's not a very big package
even compared to what we're talking
about that's only seven or eight million
lines of code more if you had something
more substantial running on that side
again like 80 I've got something like
that'd be way more lines of code
probably right so again very
conservative very low estimate of the
number of lines of code that you're
talking about here is like 55 million 56
million lines of code a very low
estimate 56 million lines of code okay
so what you can kind of see on here when
I highlight what's going on I is that
over 50 percent of this problem is
coming from nothing other than the part
you can't even get rid of right so even
before you know we could spend all day
complaining about Apache and PHP and
WordPress and my sequel and we could
spend all day having those fun
medium.com arguments about how switching
to no js' would have solved this problem
or whatever forget it we don't need to
have that argument we don't even need to
go there because even if
everything else including the browser
went to zero we haven't even reduced the
problem by half there's still an
operating system on either side of this
at least and several operating systems
in the middle if we were to be honest
right and they're not going anywhere I
don't care what new web technology
hotness you think you're using you're
still stuck with this okay so let's
think about this problem we are stuck
with a giant bloated mass underneath
absolutely everything we do and there's
nothing any of us could do about it
pretty much right I mean I'm not gonna
sit down tomorrow and write 17 million
lines of code right it is not gonna
happen and that's being conservative
right that's assuming all I wanted to do
was was do what Linux did right Windows
is probably way more it's got more
driver coverage right and all sorts of
things I don't even want to know I
really just don't but it'd be a disaster
so is that the way the world works right
is that the way the world works and the
answer is it didn't use to work that way
now this is a picture although I maybe
it doesn't look like it right now this
is a picture of like a thousand
operating systems I'm not even kidding
because in those days in the 80s and 90s
generally what happened is every time
you bought a new program on a home
computer
it came with its own custom operating
system whose job it was to run whatever
the software was because things were so
limited on those systems that all there
was was the BIOS you couldn't afford to
run another operating system at the
operation at the same time as you ran a
performance-oriented program when you
loaded doom onto your PC there was no
question that it was going to take over
the entire system
sources to run it right the original do
not the new one and prior to that in the
90s in the 1980s with things like the
amiga computer for example every game
was a boot disk it booted into its own
customized version of an operating
system that ran what it needed to run to
make its game work well and be
performant and reliable right that's
just what happened so there is no
question we have a clear and obvious
existence proof the notion that an
operating system is an unachievable goal
a fool's errand for anyone to attempt to
create we know that that is a
consequence of our times and certain
decisions by Hardware designers and
ecosystem maintainer z' and not because
there is anything intrinsically true
about it we know that in the past
hardware that was very capable and very
interesting made it so easy to create an
operating system that literally
everybody did it not a few people not
even most people but literally everybody
like I don't even remember it's like
three games I can remember that shift on
the Amiga that ran off of workbench
every other thing was a boot disk that's
just what happened okay
so now that we're in the modern era what
does it look like right well it looks
like this this is the best sort of you
know assessment I could sort of make at
the time and those two starred ones
there I think are I was sort of saying
they're going away I was right there
kind of gone now but we look at the
world of today there are effectively
three operating systems that are
consumer operating systems right so
remember here so many consumer offices I
don't even know how to enumerate them
all I don't even know
how many different ones there may have
been like I imagine
some companies reuse the same sort of
base OS code that they linked into
multiple games and others DNA I don't
even know how to count how many there
were here though because there were so
many different possible ones I just
can't even start right here I can put
them on one page and there on the left
the Windows NT kernel the Linux kernel
and the FreeBSD kernel that's it right
the Windows NT kernel run species that
are consumer-facing the Linux kernel
runs PCs that are like you know server
based or hard core you know developer
based and the FreeBSD kernel runs Apple
machines and that's it right and then I
think also the FreeBSD cone was the
PlayStation 3 &amp; 4 I put that kinda on
there but you know and that's it and
it's not even like when we went to
phones that we had a bunch of new a
persons we did right we just reused
these so the Linux kernel kind of got
you know Darwin sorry that Darwin I've
got I can't remember the name of is it
just called Android still I don't know
for making Android the Linux kernel got
repurposed for that I don't remember
what it's called the bottom the
previously kernel got turned into Darwin
for iOS right and for Matt Goss 10 and
that that's just what gets used right so
hopefully it's not there's no
exaggeration in the stuff that I've just
said it really was true that we went
from an era of a that anyone could
program their own operating system and
anyone could use a system to its fullest
extent and we transitioned from that in
the in the 90s we transition from that
to a world where none of that's true
basically no one can make an operating
system now it's a hobbyist project at
best if you do so no one will use it you
could not ship it as a piece of software
it's out of the question right so up
till say mid 90s consumer wrapping
system something that everyone could
right past the mid 90s
super wrapping system there's three and
maybe we'll never be anymore
who knows right we don't know still
waiting to find out okay so now we asked
question well why right what changed
why was this the case I mean there's got
to be a reason it doesn't seem likely
that we just went from a world where
offering systems were on no-brainer to a
world where operating systems are
something that there's no chance you
could ever possibly right and again it's
just a hobbyist or entertainment or
educational or maybe special purpose if
you're doing embedded hardware procedure
to write one and you certainly wouldn't
do it to ship a game for example that's
just absolutely ridiculous right well
let me try to suggest some reasons how
we ended up here in 1995 we introduced
USB and the concept of plug in play now
what this was is it was a wire protocol
for serial interfaces and it was spec to
sort of say well we don't really know
what's gonna be plugged into this thing
and so what we'll do is just we'll just
assume that the person who makes the
hardware will do something right
we don't know what but we'll do
something and they'll ship a piece of
hardware the other software that sits on
the other side and knows how to read the
something and write to the something
right and that was USB in 1996 we
started the transition to mandatory hard
rugged graphics right and again unlike
earlier when I say mandatory Harbor
Telegraph's I mean on the PC unlike
earlier when the when there was hard
work sorry to graphics but it was
specific to the platform so for example
the amiga computer the Atari ST the
commerce 64 all of these had things in
them that would do special purpose
graphics operations you kind of needed
them too because they were just too slow
CPU wise to do anything if you didn't
have something there to help
unlike those platforms where it was
specified what that hardware did and how
you might program it we started
introducing a new world where that was
no longer true
instead you now had mandatory hard work
centered graphics that you did not know
what it was you had a new idea could be
anything right there's just gonna be a
card in the computer with a graphics
accelerator of completely opaque design
and you're just gonna have to cross your
fingers that there's some kind of an
interface somewhere that will allow you
to do something with it and that
something will be largely dictated by
what the interface happened to spec out
and how right very similar to USB it's
like the USB of graphics basically right
and if we go back and look at this graph
you can see that there's a lesson
inflection point there right like the
complexity of Linux is going up at a
pretty reasonable rate until we hit the
introduction of these things and all of
a sudden were into no-man's land right
we then just shoot straight up the curve
and it's like an exponential curve from
that point on spiraling off into God
knows where right I can't prove that
this is why there's certainly plenty of
other other reasons it could be why but
if we think of the simplicity of the
platform and the chances that someone
could produce an operating system for it
as being sort of the wildfire that
clears out the forest if you will so
that new trees can grow and healthy
trees can grow we got rid of that
ability our forests no longer can have a
wildfire and so now we just croft on top
of cruft forever right so
now I'd like to transition from talking
about what I think the problem was and
why I think the problem is a problem to
asking the question is there something
we could do about this today right is
there a way we could go back to a eco
system that no longer had these
undesirable properties that I argue that
we now have right a eco system where if
you will if you wanted to ship a game
that you booted to right like I stuck a
USB stick in the computer and I booted
into the game so nothing else was
running let's say that I am the most
hardcore eSports person and I want to
make sure that there is literally
nothing doing anything on my platform
other than this game and it will have
the full system resources with no
interruptions and no variability I could
actually do that I could expect epic
megagames to ship me a thumb stick with
fortnight on it that I stick into the
front of my computer and boot okay do we
have any chance of seeing that world
again and I hopefully I've communicated
some reasons why we might want to see
that world again even if that's not the
end goal even if what we'd rather have
is just some better operating systems
right the answer is I think there is and
unfortunately it's not really up to
software developers to get there we can
help but unfortunately I think it's
really up to hardware people to start
taking this problem seriously and here's
why so nowadays esos es which are called
systems on a chip or SOC is the short
version right
esos es are becoming a very common very
sort of valuable to the product line
even skew for many hardware
manufacturers the drive towards
miniaturization cell phones tablet PCs
the Internet of Things
all of these trends where hardware
manufacturers are trying to get their
chips into computer devices that are not
in the traditional form factor has meant
that there's been a tremendous amount of
emphasis placed on integrating
components into single modules to
eliminate waste you look inside a PC and
you see the motherboard there's so much
crust on this thing that you'd never be
able to get it down into a phone right
and so in order to legitimately tackle
these problems of portable computing and
small form-factor computing for very
obvious reasons you need to have all of
your stuff shrunk down and minimized and
placed in into some coherent cruft free
package right well spy not cropped free
but a lot less corrupt right a lot of
the interconnects and Inter
communication needs to be simplified and
dropped down in order to get to that
point okay so this is a very common way
of designing computers now and it's
largely because of that that sort of
drive transmutation again these are not
special-purpose
they are not embedded computing for some
kind of microcontroller in something
that controls the water pressure at a
sewage treatment plant right which is
where you might have thought about this
kind of thing before it's not an
embedded microcontroller in that sense
it's literally a consumer part it's
something that goes in your phone or
your tablet right your set-top box your
television your refrigerator pretty soon
etc right because this is now the new
standard for consumer devices well guess
what it starts to
look a lot more like a home computer
from the 1980s all of the chips are
designed together packaged together
interconnected in a predictable way and
there is no configurability there aren't
two possible graphics cards that can be
on this die there's one right there
aren't two or three or four or ten
different USB controllers that could be
attached to this thing there's one right
there aren't even multiple CPUs it's
just all baked together it's all one
system and that starts to look a lot
more like a home computer from 1986
right so my proposal is what if we were
to extend the conceptual model that we
have with something like the x86 or now
x64 eisah I consider those things kind
of the same thing right to cover an
entire system on a chip all right now
the reason I make this parallel instead
of introducing a concept wholesale is
that invariably whenever you suggest the
notion that you might be able to make
the design of the hardware interface for
an entire architecture robust
predictable consistent testable and
known people act like you're saying you
want to go to the moon on the back of a
giant turtle right it's like you're
seeing something that's so far from
anything they could possibly imagine
being true or desirable or possible as
to make it ludicrous to even suggest
such a thing right if you suggest making
an ISA for those who don't know that
it's an instruction set architecture is
just a definition of how a set of memory
layouts like how a series of pieces of
data in memory are interpreted by a
piece of hardware to produce a result
right so a program an X
the x86 program that is SPECT to the x86
eisah you know if you hand it to an x86
chip it will run and it will do the same
thing on every x86 chip that's all we're
talking about so if it is just that even
to GPU vendors for just the graphics
part it is again like you were traveling
to the moon on the back of a giant
turtle so the reason that I liken it
here is because again I'm not talking
about something that is unprecedented or
weird I'm talking about something that
not only was standard but that has been
standard for decades and not only was
standard for decades but proved to be
the most valuable resource for the
company that controlled it that they
ever had so I think it's time to start
revisiting this concept and stop
thinking it's ridiculous not only is it
not ridiculous
it pays so many dividends and let me
talk to you about how that's true right
okay
what we're living in right now is a
world where the people who create the
software and the people who create the
hardware are separated by so many layers
of additional legacy or modernized
software depending on what part you're
talking about that there is no way to
test anything for performance or
reliability period and I mean that
literally there is no way to test a
piece of software in the modern world
the only way you can really hope to get
it reliable is by sending it out in the
world and fielding their rubber reports
as they come back because there are so
many configurations of things out there
there are so many different substrates
again 50 60 70 is probably low we're
probably talking about hundreds of
millions of lines of code in between the
thing you wrote right and the thing that
actually happens on the computer
contracts this with just straight x86
code that just need to compute a result
it's 100% reliable pretty much if you
just want to do a for loop that adds
some numbers together or something like
this in an x86 eisah it is almost
impossible to have that screw up the
times when it there has been mistakes
have been few and far between there's
like the Pentium divide bug or things
like that are like the only times we
have run into problems with that but in
terms of all the rest of the stuff that
surrounds that x86 eisah
it's a nightmare completely untestable
completely unreliable completely
insecure completely unmaintainable it's
all of that stuff I showed at the
beginning beginning the the crashes the
updating all of that stuff that world is
unavoidable right now I maintain because
there's so much stuff in between what
could you possibly do shipping reliable
software or performance software is very
difficult or impossible okay but if we
were to lock it down right if we were to
say no we're going to settle on a
specific eisah
it gets revised every couple of years by
making some additions to it just like
the x86 x64 eisah
it goes through revisions every so often
but we all
move to them in a wave as they become
accepted by the mainstream harbour
market the payoffs would be immense
suddenly you could test that something
that ran the same on your system would
rant run the same an eye on someone
else's system you wouldn't be guessing
anymore
right you would know because there
wouldn't be tons and tons of variable
state software in between in various
states of update for various different
types of things that interpret things
differently right bugs would actually be
real bugs in the hardware that would be
embarrassing for the companies who ship
them and they would have to introduce
actual compliance like intel does to
make sure that they ship things that
actually worked and after that point any
bug that actually occurs is a bug in
your software that you shipped and it's
something you could fix and something
you could have tested the user is no
longer running a random stack of 60
million lines of code in addition to the
hundred thousand you shipped they're
just running the hundred thousand you
shipped and if it worked on your machine
it works on their machine okay we're
already seeing indications of what even
tiny steps in this direction would bring
in terms of efficiency reliability
security performance all these sorts of
things right around the time that I was
giving this lecture in 2015 people were
talking about mantle what was mantle
nothing special it's just a simple way
of talking to AMD cards that's closer to
what their driver actually was already
doing right I and hey lo and behold when
you got the AMD driver out of the way
all of a sudden the exact same piece of
hardware performed way way better right
here are the performance increases that
we're seeing just from getting rid of
the Radian driver that's all that
happened and not even all of it just
part of it right so 50 percent
more performance from getting rid of bad
code that sat between you and the
hardware that's all that happened you
didn't buy a new graphics card you
didn't rewrite your engine you just
finally got a chance to program the
thing closer to what it actually was
right imagine if you took that to the
next step and said look you don't even
need any driver at all
forget mantle here's just how you
download code to a GPU and run it again
more reliability you take code out of
the pipe it becomes more symmetric
between the user's machine and yours the
efficiency goes up the reliability goes
up and of course the security goes up
because the less lines of code there are
the less exploit parts there are right
every one of those 100 million lines of
code or who even knows how many there
are now in between your app and your
hardware is an exploit possibility every
single one of those can have an
exploitable bug in it every time you
remove one you are removing a
possibility for a virus or a hacker to
do something untoward with your system
right now that's on the left the mantle
performance on the right is a great
paper I recommend everyone read it it
was actually came out when I was making
this lecture and I was like yes this is
what I've been thinking and basically
what it was is saying hey what if we
just made the operating system be a
thing that all it does is broker access
to the hardware but otherwise we let the
hardware be almost directly programmable
as much as we can and they could only
really do this as sort of a simple test
because they couldn't modify the
hardware but what they found was when
they made this modification and made
sort of a prototype version of it based
off of Linux where they stripped things
out and made special pathways to test
this they found that the performance
they got over straight Linux was
dramatic right the amount of network
processing that's what they were testing
like network packet processing stuff
like that that they could achieve over
the Linux kernel was nuts right
just absolutely nuts and again nothing
different happened the computer didn't
change all they did was effectively
delete bad code from the from the pipe
they just got rid of it and so the the
benefits to everyone of removing code
from a system cannot be overstated
everything gets better when the code
gets smaller pretty much across the
board so if we actually wanted to start
pursuing this as a real path right going
down this road and saying how do we
maybe get to a future where hardware as
a rule is designed under a set of
guidelines that say here is the memory
that you take in and here is the memory
that you put out and that's your job you
don't get a driver right you don't get
one there's no such thing as a driver a
hardware company ships Hardware you
don't get to ship software if you want
to ship software it's gonna have to be
on the hardware itself and we're not
gonna update it so it better be really
good right and again people freaked out
at that suggestion
that's what Intel does every day right
that is what happens with the x86 eisah
right or the XS t4i so now is it harder
yes but that should be the job that
should be what a hardware company is is
producing reliable hardware right and
Plus once you demand that as a minimum
bar everyone's on a on a level playing
field right if everyone has to meet that
bar then nobody has to worry about the
fact that they can't cheat in their
driver and do these other things because
no one can cheat so you pretty much have
to just do it whatever you're gonna do
has to be done in the hardware right and
you're all playing on a level playing
field then because it has to be done in
hardware okay so how do we
get here what we essentially need are
these sort of six points that I've
listed here to get to direct coding
right we need to first get the
compatibility which is specking out
something like an ice ax that will be
maintained by hardware vendors we have
to have performance reasonable enough
that people could start using this for
real right and why do I say that
well you can get your hands on a fully
documented ISOs SOC today for example
the Raspberry Pi there's a few parts in
our document but even the Broadcom chip
is now fully documented the graphics
part rather there is a little bit of
startup code that's not documented but I
think that's the only thing so you can
go get your hands on a Raspberry Pi
today and have that compatibility
guarantee with other raspberry PI's
right but a Raspberry Pi is simply not a
good enough piece of hardware for anyone
to use it for anything real in a
consumer setting right you're not gonna
ship player unknowns battlegrounds on
the Raspberry Pi so in order to start
being something we could take seriously
as computing platform it has to be real
hardware it has to be a geforce 1080
that's made to some eisah
it can't be some old part that nobody
wants anymore that just we happen to
know a lot of program that's not enough
right third thing it needs to be simple
right you can't just take and say oh hey
good news what we did is we took the G
first 1080 we moved our entire gigantic
driver with all of its programming
substrate and we put it into a ROM on
the thing and now you just send like
Vulcan commands to it right it's like no
that's not what we're talking about here
we have to get back to saying look we
write some memory we read to some memory
that's how the interface works right
it's like it used to be there isn't some
kind of a weird like you know you need
10 million lines of code to access the
ice because that's how much there is or
something right it has to go back to
being a sense of the design obviously we
need documentation
and tutorials for it so people can learn
how to use it and use it well and then
finally we need some publicity to say
look this is something people should buy
some people should use so there's a lot
of stuff since it's hard don't get me
wrong
it's a very difficult path to go down
because it takes a lot of people to
believe it should be done I don't
actually think there's anything hard
about it in the difficult to do it's
more about commitment less about
difficulty but so I kind of split it up
here between you meaning hardware
vendors because that's who this talk was
originally designed for and us meaning
the people who program right and have to
you know would use it and so I think we
split up those six things they break
down very cleanly hardware designers
need to be like actually determine
themselves to agree on an SOC right and
that's to see architecture then they
have to start shipping something like
they're really good parts need to follow
that SOC and they need to commit to
simplifying the way that it's used to
just read write memory write rewrite
memory in mailboxes or whatever that
Arrakis paper that I pointed that I
referenced has a really good example of
how to do say a NIC that just uses ring
buffer only hardware interfaces and
mailboxes to achieve everything it needs
to achieve that's the kind of thing we
need right
and so hardware designs you to do that
obviously surfers on can help with that
but they can only help by saying whether
or not these interfaces are going to be
good enough and simple enough to
actually be programmable in a realistic
way but there's nothing else they can do
all the rest of it is up to getting some
at least one or two hardware developers
to actually buy in and try to do
something like this now for our part our
part we can do as soon as we have
anything even like that right we can
help with the ring buffer design like I
said we can help design something that
satisfies our need to be able to develop
things that are reliable and easy to
understand and so on but that also meet
the demands that the hardware has
because the harbor can only do certain
things obviously but beyond that we can
do everything else
make prototype OS is for it we can
document it we can ship libraries right
we can make all kinds of libraries that
programs could use to run on top of this
if they wanted to so that people who
don't want understand it don't have to
understand it it's always you know
strictly optional things that that look
like DirectX on top or OpenGL on top or
Vulcan on top so if you already know one
of those you can just program to that
still right so that there isn't a lot of
friction in terms of moving over to it
and then finally you know we need a lot
of people to be excited about this but I
think we can do that right I think the
response to handmade hero is kind of
demonstrated that there are a lot of
people are interested in this sort of
thing they just don't have anywhere to
go and they don't have any way to
contribute right they don't have any way
to help push us towards a future where
hardware is something we can actually
directly program nobody can really do
that on the software side of things but
if hardware developers gave us an
opportunity to do so we would I know I
would and I know lots of people who
watch this show would and I know lots of
people who don't watch this show would I
know there's a lot of people out there
who want to see something like this
happen and would be ecstatic to start
contributing to something that could get
us there and so what I think we would do
for first steps right used to try to get
back to the original Linux right to try
and say if we were gonna start Linux
today the original Linux I think was
20,000 lives of assembly code right if
we were gonna redo that today 20,000
lines of assembly code is something a
single individual can write okay it's
not that hard to do
how do we get to a piece of hardware
that has a well enough simple enough
spec interface that you can make the
equivalent of the original 1991 Linux in
20,000 lines of assembly language that's
just now on a modern part
how do we get there because I absolutely
do not believe that you can't do it we
just didn't want to
we just kept adding complexity to the
hardware interface and adding more and
more drivers because that was the path
of least resistance and it was what
allowed companies to go off on their own
and not have to talk to anyone to agree
on how something would be designed right
that's why we did it but I fundamentally
don't believe there's anything different
about today's Hardware fundamentally
that you couldn't make an operating
system in 20,000 lines again if the
hardware was designed more sense we
could have all the same features it has
today it just needs to be designed more
sensibly and I think we could do that I
think we just look to see how do we get
20,000 lines of Azzam to drive a
hypothetical piece of hardware that does
what today's hardware does right how do
we get that and that's something a
hardware company can start working on
that's something that Intel could start
doing tomorrow right they've got SOC s
that have graphics built in what does
the interface to that huge substrate
which I guarantee you takes way more
than 20,000 lines of Azzam to probably
get an operating system up and running
on one these things right why there are
researchers at Intel right now who could
answer that why what is wrong with the
design of the interfaces to these chips
that they require so much extra work how
do we get it down so it's the same as
Linux was what can we simplify because I
know that we can and then from that
answer we can move on to an initial
attempt at in ISE I say something that
simplifies the network interface I mean
it simplifies the SATA interface and it
simplifies USB interface and it
simplifies the video interface right
because fundamentally all of these
things are just the CPU writing to some
memory and kicking it off and then
looking for memory that comes back
that's fundamentally all that really is
happening here why can't we get it down
to that
what's stopping us right and then I
contend once we've got it to something
fairly straightforward like that where
you can just look at data definitions
and say you write this data in here and
kick it off this is what the chip does
right that is very tractable any
programmer understands how to get that
working right and it opens up a whole
new set of possibilities
should we keep simplifying from there
and keep making it so that we keep
getting more and more straightforward
and direct ways to talk to Hardware and
have them do things so that the data
that we're actually sending them makes
more and more sense in that and the
things they execute make more sense sure
right which would it be great if we
continued to improve the x64 ISO to make
it simpler and more whatever but right
it's always good to do that yes but just
getting to a place of possibility
doesn't require all that we just need to
get rid of the obvious Croft and I
guarantee you 90% of the problem the way
is obvious Croft not super hard
technical problems all right so now I'd
like to sort of introduce two possible
hypothetical situations right and I sort
of wanted to to posit these in a way
that would say motivate a company such
as Intel for example as to why even for
a commercial hardware vendor with a
vested interest in what they're
currently shipping why might they care
about this right uh so the first would
if set is negative what if Linus
Torvalds later right
sorry Linus Torvald right Linux would
never have happened there's no way he
was gonna write a massive thing like
there's no way he would have written a
system that could have handled like all
the USB stuff and all the graphic stuff
that we currently do today no one would
want to use this operating system that
he started with it wouldn't be useful to
anyone for any purpose right
so Linux never
would have been a thing that took off
and as a consequence we would literally
have a single PC operating system right
a single one
it just be Windows every last thing you
take for granted right now that was made
possible because of Linux would not have
happened all servers would be controlled
by Microsoft all of them right every
last thing every desktop computer
controlled by Microsoft you would
possibly still have had Apple but it's
unclear whether you actually would have
or not because at that time again there
was a bunch of other options available
thanks to Linux and the ecosystem that
had it had created so it's unclear what
Mac OS 10 would have done and I don't
know
so maybe would have still had an apple
niche but it certainly wouldn't been
server and so you would literally be
looking at a world where all pretty much
all PC but definitely all server was
controlled by Microsoft
most of what we take for granted on the
internet today would not have happened
the way that it happened and with one
for-profit company in control of all of
it you have to ask yourself what would
this world look like right number two is
what if there is going to be another
another Linus in the future but what if
instead of doing it on say an Intel
piece of hardware or an AMD piece of
hardware what if they do it on something
like arm right what if there is a
different platform that they pick
because that platform was simpler had a
more coherent eye so who knows what
happened right and the answer is that
entire lineage of computing that entire
direction of computing that could
develop from that you will make zero
money on and furthermore all of the uses
is that your computing chips could have
would have been doing that migrate to
this new platform you will not make
money on any of them right no x64
processor will be involved in any of
that lineage because that's not where it
started right so again the benefits of
being the hardware people who start to
move in this direction might be very
important and missing out on a trend
like that could be very serious the
reason that Intel sells all of their
server chips right now is because linus
torvalds started out programming on an
x64 well the next thirty x86 right
that's why so that whole lineage grew up
around that if it had grown up around
something else x86 would have been the
port platform it would have been like a
dec alpha or something like that who
knows if it ever would have taken off
maybe it wouldn't have got supported
maybe no one would have cared and then
all of the chips that Intel sells in
that market right now for example that
money just isn't there right high margin
very important chips nobody wants them
they'd rather have these arm chips
because that's everyone knows that's
what Linux runs best on is these arms or
something right
who knows so then let's get to the
positive I'm pathetic goals which are
like what if we do embrace more of this
SOC thing what what are the dividends
that could be paid there right so first
of all what if making actually for our
system was as easy as making an
application right and that's the world
of 1980s it's so easy to make an
operation that everyone who made a game
did it right if that were the case think
of how many options we would have for
defining the future of computing right
Microsoft's stranglehold on PCs would
evaporate immediately right because
there'd be so many alternatives that you
could never there be no way for a
operating system company to sit on their
laurels and ship such lackluster things
right
they would get out competed pretty much
instantaneously and that's great for
everybody more competition in the OS
face means that our OS doesn't have to
be so bad like it is right now right but
it's never gonna happen any other way
you're stuck with Linux and and Windows
right now that's not changing if the
hardware doesn't change first okay so
another what if what if running software
on x64 required no OS and they were just
tied to the exit of our hardware not to
an OS right I mean this is a real
possible future
what if they're the only OS on your
system at all was just basically a
hypervisor it was just a thing that
switched between full programs that just
ran directly on top of the hardware
right now all of a sudden x64 is king of
the hill right now Windows is king of
the hill doesn't really matter that
something's written for x64 anymore all
that much right it matters it's written
to the Windows api's or the browser's
api's right that's what matters
that's what determines what runs where
ok and it determines furthermore who has
the entrenched advantage x64 chip
vendors have entrenched an advantage of
running x64 code how much of that is
there out there not that much anymore
why because it's not the hard part of
the problem producing the CPU code is
not the hard part of RAM it's all the
drivers it's all the infrastructure
necessary to run the rest of the
hardware the mouse input the keyboard
input talking the printers all that
stuff right that's the thing that
actually determines who controls the
ecosystem is that substrate and
increasingly now that's like w3c right
and that makes x64 or whatever your
hardware part is irrelevant nobody cares
what you spec and nobody is enticed to
run on your platform because who cares
as long as someone ported the web
browser you're done right
so if a group of web group of hardware
developers did go in this direction it
could pay enormous dividends because
they would be the people who would be
able to sell the chips and people not
producing chips that comply with this
isuh
would be at a massive disadvantage there
are huge potential payoffs for going
this way early if it did take off
because now you're in a great position
to be the leaders in shipping stings
that comply to this isuh
right because as software gets written
closer to the isit you become the
platform not the w3c right or whoever
else it happens to be at the time so
it's actually very good for a hardware
people it's a very advantageous position
and furthermore it's something that
allows you to provide real games to your
customers right now if I was someone
working at Intel or AMD I'd be pulling
my hair out because I'm like the only
people I know how to get any performance
improvements to are like game developers
right there's nothing like this this web
browsers and that spec is such a
disaster there's nothing I can do right
I shipped someone this new core i9 chip
and this is just as bad as experience as
if they were running on the i3 right it
doesn't matter because there's so much
cruft in the way and it's so divorced
from the hardware that it just doesn't
matter I can't really help you you know
that I can't really provide those real
performance gains because it's unclear
what I would even target at this point
right whereas if things are directly
running on a nexus t4 you could have
this power to ship huge improvements
every time because the software is
literally just running on top of your
stuff and when you improve it everything
improves and the things that people can
ship that year are twice as good as the
things they could ship the previous year
for reals and that's not a world we've
been living in for a very long time
except on basically GPU code for games
it's really we're the only place we've
been seeing that right and finally as a
positive hypothetical for companies like
Intel or companies like Samsung
you've got great fab technology what if
that was what determined market
leadership right we all know we're going
to be using this isuh
so wouldn't you like it that the person
who builds the best hardware wins isn't
that the best right whereas right now
you're rapidly moving towards a world
where nobody cares for consumer
operating systems nobody cares I don't
know which ships in this computer don't
care right or whatever is what most
people would think they really just
can't even perceive the difference a lot
of times now you buy a new laptop it
feels exactly same as your old laptop
right that's no good for a hardware
company what are you gonna sell people
how are you gonna convince an upgrade
right these are real problems you need
to make ways for people to program and
use the hardware for real because simply
increasing the clock rate doesn't really
work anymore right we've passed that
that heat point and so you need to offer
your customers something we can help you
offer your cup you're off offer
customers those things if you actually
give us a way to program the hardware
for real and again just look at the
console market to see that that's true
game developers who work on console
hardware do amazing things with that
hardware that is so much better than
what they could do with the hardware
normally because they can exploit all
the stuff because they know effectively
the eisah right so that's the end of the
talk I hope that gave some perspective
on what I think the problems are why I
think their problems and what could be
done to fix those problems but in short
the TLDR of it right is just we know we
have a better opportunity because we had
it in 1980 right we had it in the 80s we
lost it in the 90s and now we're living
in a world without it I think we can get
back there and I think there are real
reasons we
want to for everyone's sake not just
people who love computing and who love
Hardware aren't in programming but just
the ability to unleash all of the people
who care about that kind of programming
to let them actually start doing real
work again those people will produce the
libraries and the and the system
services and the documentation and the
tutorials they'll produce the substrate
that will allow everyone on top to excel
so it doesn't even matter that it's only
10% of the programmers who can really do
something down there maybe because it's
really a type of program that only
certain people enjoy or certain people
are good at even that's okay because
those people just need to be given the
chance and we've already seen that they
will much like Linus did share what they
create with the world in beneficial ways
but right now they cannot do that they
cannot help you and I think you really
do want them to and I don't think it's
just altruistic I don't think it's just
sort of a fanciful thing I think it
could pay real dividends both in terms
of the quality of the computing
experience that we will have in the
future but also in terms of real actual
monetary benefits for commercial
companies if they were to go this route
if even a small consortium of major
hardware vendors decided to go this
route and start shipping a platform with
a stable eisah that people could
directly program to I think
wouldn't take more than five to ten
years for us to really start seeing real
dividends from that thing all the way
from that being the new obvious answer
to things like consoles and set-top
boxes so I can get major design wins
there but just to the fact that you
could it could assure in a real
revolution in in real home computing
that we can't even predict how many
positive outcomes there may be from it
positive outcomes like the one we had
when Y
made Linux that has I think by anyone's
estimation radically changed the face of
computing for the better because without
Linux I think we would have been living
in a much worse world
I don't think Linux can happen again
without hardware vendors changing the
way they do things and I think for all
of our benefits they should I want to
see Linux happen again and I think they
can make it happen so please consider it
and know that there's tons of us out
here who are ready to help you and jump
on that bandwagon if the time comes so
thanks very much for listening and I'm
happy to take questions now from the
stream
our rift asks is include OS going in the
right direction
it does not contain the OS only your
program except for a bootloader
I have not looked at it because I know
about that but from your description it
sounds exactly like the kind of thing
that I'm talking about right and
similarly like hypervisors are sort of
in this direction as well in the sense
that like although they can't because
the hardware underneath is too
complicated they can't really provide
the kind of thing that we really want
for a consumer experience where it has
the full capability of running a
graphics driver easily and all that sort
of stuff right they kind of only saw
like a little bit of the problem but
they are going in that correct direction
in a sense right
the tephra foe do you have any returns
since you made that talk so I only gave
the talk to a very small number of
people at Intel
it was well-received and I did end up
talking to a vice-president there about
it but at the end of the day what I sort
of gathered from it was that in order to
really ever get something done I had a
major hardware vendor you need to create
a really big public demand for something
which is why I was like let me just give
this thing publicly I mean to do it for
a while and the reason I said just
because they have so much riding on
their hardware and it cost so much to
produce that even if something sounds
like a good idea and they agree with it
it's unclear to them that they can
generate the kinds of internal momentum
necessary to get it to actually happen
and I don't fault them for that I think
being a hardware company is not like
being a software
company being a hardware company is very
you must be very risk-averse
because fabbing a chip designing and
Fabio chip is an incredibly expensive
process on the order that we cannot
really comprehend in software because we
don't deal with the day-to-day uh and so
they are right to be cautious and I
don't blame them but we need them to go
in this direction I believe and so the
question to me is how do we generate the
momentum inside their companies to make
it happen how do we help them generate
that momentum because it's not their
fault it's not like even if we all agree
this was right it's not their fault it's
not happening because they need market
pressure they need external pressure
external demand to become obvious to
lots of people that company before they
can really put those initiatives in
place and so the reason I say it's a
collaborative effort is in the software
community we need to figure out ways we
can start to really articulate why this
is important and show the demand needs
to be there and show what the road map
looks like
because hardware companies can't just do
this on a whim they can't just go oh
yeah that I saw that talk buy case
meritorious sound like a good idea let's
go simplify the interface and then put
out chip it's like that's not the
reality of hardware right so I do think
it was received well and I do think it
will be received well at hardware
companies I just think it's not that
simple the people at the hardware
companies to agree with it can't just
start doing it they need a lot of buy-in
and they need a lot of external obvious
buy and these are publicly traded
companies with a lot on the line with
incredibly expensive processes that they
can't just dedicate to you know sort of
a a pet project that people think is
good
have I seen read ops OS and it's it's
20k lakh MINIX um again I want to be
clear about the 20,000 line thing it's
not that hard to make a small x86
operating system or x64 operating
in twenty thousand lines of code right
it won't do anything right it won't run
a 3d game it won't support most printers
or keyboards or video webcams right
because all of that stuff is the cruft
and so making an X 64 operating system
that's just running X 64 code that
doesn't interface with any external
devices or that still uses the VGA
aperture to draw a console hasn't gotten
any harder since 1991 really XE before
is nominally a bit harder than x86 to
get started up I believe but it's not
really that much different su OS is
right now there are 20,000 lines of code
but that don't do that don't have
running 3d graphics at full speed
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah right like all
that stuff that's the hard part the hard
part is getting the consumer parts in
there and so that's what the thing is
that we need to focus on it's that part
right so I just want to be clear on that
because there are small OSS out there
that don't really support modern
consumer features and that's the problem
what can someone who isn't a hardware
vendor do towards this cause I think
again it's about us trying to create and
publicize this sort of understanding of
the problem understanding that a 30
million line at minimum barrier between
a developer and their user is not
tenable and that the reason our
computing experiences today are so bad
is because of it right I think sort of
pushing this narrative forwards and
understanding that this is a problem
that needs solving and we need hardware
developers to help us solve it I think
that's what we can do as the first step
and once we start getting people
thinking it's a
it needs to solve then we can move on to
thinking about how we solve it but right
now I think the problem is is also I
want some meta problem people need to
start understanding how bad this
situation is they can feel it because
when you use a PC today it's a nightmare
right but we need to start articulating
why and we need to articulating the path
forward and so that needs to start
happening what about security should
that be part of a new OS or built into
hardware somehow directly so I would
actually argue that security is
something that actually can be made much
more robust in the world that I'm
talking about and here's why let's
suppose we go to a system that's very
similar to the 1980 system right where
and this is a hyperbole I don't think
this is where we want to end up but I'm
just going to give you an example it
would have been incredibly different
difficult to write a virus that attacked
a game on the Amiga computer because
every new game was completely different
and ran in a very different way right so
the viruses that typically attacked that
computer actually at a much harder time
with anything that was doing a custom OS
the things that it tended to attack were
the standard OS the workbench one that
shipped with it right and so I think in
today's world I think there's a real
parallel to that let's suppose that you
had a separate way of writing to the
disk and a separate way of like a
completely compartmentalized wholly run
thing that the ISO just boots to right
that is the web browser you use to go on
and do your banking and when you want to
do something else you boot out of it
it's gone and nobody even knows what the
that that segment of the drive isn't
isn't even accessible to anyone else
because that segment of the drive was
written by that thing and it's the only
thing that even knows where
or what formats in or whatever right
that is actually a world where security
breaches are way harder than they used
to be because now you have to deal with
so much variability you're essentially
making the virus writers task way harder
right the more compartmentalised you
make a program and the less things it
uses and relies on that are known to be
standard the harder the virus authors
job is so actually I would say that all
of the security program problems we have
today in a new world like I'm talking
about we would already get way less even
before we started talking about what to
do in addition to them for security
purposes because not having everything
run on a giant essentially 60 million
line exploit target right removes a huge
number of the potential ways people
break into systems so that's a great
feature it's not all we want to do yes
for security we'd want to start thinking
about how do you push how do you make
that eisah
be as secure as possible by design but I
think even before you start doing that
you've gotten into a better place than
we are today
we'll just talking about on YouTube yes
include OS runs on C++ what about
programming languages issue I guess I'm
not sure what you mean about that stuff
I don't know much about I don't know
anything about include OS but what I was
going to say is I don't think
programming languages are an issue here
at all the benefit of an ice ax is it is
an ice ax it defines the memory format
for the things that the hardware can do
and so any language can now compile to
it is the same as X 64 X 64 it doesn't
matter what program lines you use do you
want to use c-sharp great you want to
use C++ great do you want to use ML
fantastic do you want to run in
JavaScript well you're an interpreter
but no problem that interpreter can run
on exit to four as well right
20 years go go nuts right and so I think
that an ice ax is great because it it
just says here's what I have to happen
data wise in memory and with this is
what the data have to look like in
memory for the CPU the SOC to do things
and I don't care how it got there right
you can do whatever you want you can get
that data you can produce that data from
any utility you want and so every
language can support it if it wants to
any language that wants to make a
back-end you know clan can just make a I
mean LLVM can make a back-end for it and
then anything that clan can take can do
it right I have I had a chance to
evaluate Agner Foggs I said I haven't
but I don't think that's the kind of ice
I'm talking about thats just an ice ax
for CPUs am I wrong
I don't think it's for the system if the
system that we need I don't think X 64
is fundamentally a problem are there
things you'd probably change about X's
before if you wanted to make it better
absolutely do I think that's the problem
no it's very stable we can use
I don't think it needs a lot of
modification it's not the big part of
the problem today the big part of the
problem today is all the stuff that's
not x16 the exes before eisah how the
USB controller is programmed how the
graphics controller is programs how the
you know something if there's anything
else in particular I don't think there
is I think if you had the USB and
graphics controller you'd be pretty much
a pretty far bit of the way there but
for smaller code you need reusability
and for reusability you need generic
programming programmers are not used to
writing generic code and companies don't
care about reusability as long as they
ship features do you think generic
parent should be taught in practice mark
I disagree with with that just even this
the premise generic code is usually
larger not smaller smaller code is
usually because it was specific right
and so I think the important thing to
understand is like hey in the DOS days
if you wanted to initialize the graphics
card you put two values into two
registers and you trigger the interrupts
that is setting up the graphics card
nowadays you need to make like a billion
OpenGL calls right or Vulcan calls or
whatever right that non sort of
conciseness of the programmability is
what leads to the problem and it's not
really about generic programming can you
give an example of how the interface
would be simpler for your common
programmer sure that das example I just
gave is is a very good example right
initializing something by doing two mobs
and an INT is so far removed from how
you have to initialize a graphics card
today in terms of programmer time and
energy that it's insane right and the
problem hasn't really gotten that much
harder I know people think it has but it
hasn't really especially as GPUs become
programmable a lot of what you do with
them is just uploading bytecode for them
to run right now byte codes the wrong
term compiled you know code for their
machine language right
and the control of them is not that
complicated and could be simplified
further if we got back to that that's
all you would do when you needed to
initialize a graphics card you wouldn't
need tons of libraries and drivers and
all these other things in your way
because fundamentally speaking it's just
not that hard of a problem
not much harder to set up six written
through it just one more step yeah I
mean like I said it's um it's very minor
right you just have to do a little bit
to get yourself in a 64-bit mode and yes
the talk will be watchable on YouTube
internal static voice oh do you propose
that we should make a chip that doesn't
spark as your feature or features that
consumer expects no what I'm suggesting
is we need to just take so for example
we already have chips that are almost
what we want right so for example a lot
of laptops that consumers actually use
today have their CPU and their GPUs
supplied by Intel on a single die right
the core i7 for example had the GPU
welded onto it and it's got an own
programming
eisah on it right the difference is that
ice ax is not stable from generation to
generation and it's not particularly
well designed but fundamentally speaking
that's already what we're talking about
a core i7 chip was almost what we need
hardware wise it just wasn't necessarily
designed at the interface level to be
something that's particularly usable but
it could have been
do you think that maybe the reason that
some of the suffer and driver has become
our bloated and some of the code pests
or larger is because the hardware is
more complicated than it used to be as
well no I actually don't think that's
true
I think the hardware is actually simpler
now than it used to be in a lot of ways
I don't think that you can look at
something like an Amiga computer and
think that it was particularly simple it
was still rather complicated and
programming it well was actually pretty
tricky at some level if you really did
want to get it was a fairly high point
in programming complexity I think
nowadays GPUs are actually very
programmable and a lot of what they do
just looks like executing machine code
like a CPU would do right it's not that
special purpose and that is why I think
we're getting I wouldn't have
recommended this path in the year 2000
because things were still so TWiki
special-purpose and changing so rapidly
that I don't think it would have made
any sense to settle on an ice ax
nowadays GPUs are becoming almost just
other CPUs right and I think if we just
started to look at it as a unified ice
ax it actually can be quite simple even
compared to old computers we used to
program directly and again that's only
because we have gotten to a place where
these things became general-purpose
because they had to in order to support
the kinds of workloads we wanted right
they are continuing ever as we go GPUs
have steadily gotten less and less like
it they used to be very much like an
Amiga chip all kinds of crazy
special-purpose stuff right and that's
all they could do no general purpose
right and as they go they've gotten much
simpler and when I say simpler I don't
mean in terms of their capabilities I
mean in terms of their difference from
an x64 right a modern GPU is now very
close to an x64 chip it used to be
nothing like one and standardizing on an
instruction set for one might have been
a really silly idea at that time right
so I think that it's it's really that's
not the explanation I think the reason
that software and drivers come are
bloated is because of the route we took
to get there and make no mistake it may
have been necessary to go that route it
may have been very good for us to have a
time in computing history when it was
crazy cruft in between mushy almost
barely working stuff that anyone could
swap in and out because that allowed the
hardware to experiment a lot and we
needed that until we started realizing
that GPUs are gonna be basically CPUs we
needed that right but now that we're
kind of starting to converge I think the
time has come to start looking towards
an ice ax again right so I don't think I
I'm not trying to make any arguments
that we did the wrong thing then maybe
it was the right thing for its time I
think it needs to come back around just
the world you're promoting me in the end
or at least a big decrease in
interoperability if so wouldn't that
make developing applications much harder
across multiple systems no it means the
opposite of that the reason I suggest
that means the opposite of that is for
example take the current situation today
where you want to ship a game on a PC
and on a Mac right now that is an
incredibly difficult proposition
actually most people who want to do it
do absolutely ridiculous stuff to make
that happen either they use a huge
abstraction library to separate them
from the problem and that abstraction
library has two totally different
compilation paths one for Apple and one
for PC or they do hilarious things like
use a DirectX emulation layer on their
apple part that silently transcodes it
to metal right so the interoperability
is actually awful today it's very very
bad you pretty much need two completely
different executables for Apple on PC
what I would point out it's the same
computer it's the exact same computer
you've got the same
force card and the same Intel chip in
the Apple computer as you have in the PC
yet you need a completely different
program on both to run if on the other
hand the ice ax was on the hardware
level you just took the same program
both OSS could just run the same program
you'd be done right interoperability
would be a little harder for things that
want to use a window manager so non full
screen but for games you just ship the
same package every game that shipped on
a PC would just run on a Mac you'd be
done right so actually it's the opposite
having a hardware eisah can only
increase the chances that you will be
able to interoperate not the other way
around cuz the world we live in today is
the one where you have no
interoperability and the only way to get
portability is to run on top of a huge
stack of libraries the world I'm talking
about you can still do that you can
still run on a huge stack of libraries
if you want to right because it's the
same you could but you also now have the
option of not doing that and it could
run in multiple places even when you
don't so it's if anything increases the
interoperability it can never decrease
it because you always have the
opportunity what you did before which is
just have a huge pile of libraries
underneath you so if you want that you
can still do it right nothing would stop
you
isn't that what Android and I believe
iOS do sorry I'm not sure what the thing
is that you're referring to probably
because it was asked a while back in a
world where every program runs its own
OS how do you handle running two
programs simultaneously or am i
misunderstanding so you may be
misunderstanding slightly again what I'm
suggesting is not that we need a world
where everyone writes their own OS
because you don't really need to do that
for any particular purpose and it's
totally fine to write something that
isn't running on its own OS right but
there's two inches that question one if
we do want a world where every program
runs on its own OS we can do that using
something like a hypervisor right that's
what a hypervisor is today
it's how datacenters work right it's how
things work where you have multiple os's
that need to maybe run on this shared
computing device that timeshares
depending on who is loaded on it at the
time so we have a solution to that
problem it's ring -1 in an intel chip or
whatever you want to call it we have a
switch in that problem so we can run two
programs simultaneously or more if we
want to and swap between them based on
which one we're trying to use but I'm
not even advocating that I don't think
we need a world where every programmer
writes or of an OS it's not necessary
what I am advocating is a world in which
anyone who wants to write an OS can
write because that's how we get
ourselves out of this world of very
restrictive poor-performing OS is that
have to be huge as well and are very
unreliable right so being put in a
position where we can innovate on OS as
easily and also where the OS itself is
not thought of as a big deal right it's
just oh what OS are you running out it
doesn't really matter that much right
because the services the OS provides are
very minimal at that point you're right
right now the services the OS provides
are imperative and maximal without the
OS is graphics drivers USB driver disk
driver Network driver without all that
stuff in place you can't even make a
barely functioning program right but in
the future when you didn't need any of
those things the OS isn't really that
relevant and you could run the same
program potentially on many different
OSS without a big without it being a big
deal for example
so if we were to move towards more of a
hired hardware specified world it just
opens up a lot of possibilities and you
don't have to use those possibilities
everywhere having them be available
though is critical and it's critical for
that competition and experimentation so
you're opposed there's new multitasking
because if you start separating
applications you will start to get all
the requirements of modern opera systems
over time um sue yes and no right
there's a couple of things that I would
point out about that one is that at the
moment people make very low use of
multitasking they make such low use of
multitasking that things like Android
and and iOS support it in a very light
and restrictive fashion right so if you
look at how people actually use their
systems multitasking is not as relevant
as you might think but let me put that
in some into some context here to the
extent that you want multitasking at
least for example the way I use it is
usually partitioned it's partitioned
into two things one there are background
tasks that I may want to run and then
there is the application I'm actually
using right and to a large extent that
is the that is all I really want my
hypervisor or OS to do right maybe I
want to download something in the
background but other than that I really
don't want my computer to be doing
anything other than what I'm actually
doing right now right so there are some
things we you may want to run in the
background and then most your computing
research you want to be noted to one
thing getting to a place where that is a
more sensible thing rather than the
current mode of multitasking where
there's just tons of crap running on my
aperture system at all times I would
actually say a more restrictive version
of multitasking would actually be a good
thing that said that's my opinion and I
don't think my opinion is the important
part here having different os's for
different purposes is what I want
I want an OS that works the way I just
said and I'd love you to have an OS that
works the way you want right getting
down to an ice ax where a program can be
written without thought to the OS it was
running on would be a huge win for that
right because furthermore you could have
a sort of standardized OS layer a
minimal one on top of that we could
innovate on whereas any OS that you know
something like POSIX right if you wanted
to make something that was like the new
POSIX here is a standard we architected
it well we really thought about it
here's the thing you can write
applications - that's the minimum
library necessary to talk to an OS right
and in everything that's hardware
related you can just do directly on the
hardware we broker it a little bit but
that's it right much like Arrakis that
paper I reference please read it it's
very good if we did a minimal thing like
that that we all agreed on then everyone
could write OS is that rain everyone's
software right because now there's no
chance of that
because there's so much disagreement
about how you would even drive the
hardware that there's no chance of it
but once you take all of that out of it
you realize the Syst the services an
operating system should be delivering to
you are so small that we could just
probably agree on them in something like
POSIX again how do I know this because
we used to do it back when hardware is
designed sensibly we had stuff like a
fairly small substrate of how you would
do things a vt100 terminal spec was all
you really need if it's right I don't
think we're fundamentally that far away
from that I think we let ourselves get
that far away because of the driver
nightmare but I think we can move away
from it and once you move away from it
you start to lose a lot of these
compatibility issues that you're talking
about
that's our look you so all we really
need is for us be to be in the ice ax
and CPUs with enough course to be GPU
for the GPU Deer Island we don't even
need that right you can have a CPU and
GPU just make the GPU be a standard
programmable spec that that stays
compatible as you move forward that's
all we need we don't need to replace
GPUs GPUs can still play their purpose
you can have a heterogeneous computing
environment again the Amiga was a
heterogeneous computing environment it
had a CPU and a GPU and an APU an audio
processing unit right and so it's not at
all about removing the GPU from the
equation or removing USB from the
creation
it's about standardizing on interfaces
to them that are hardware based and
saying we're going to accept the
limitation of that going forward right
and so the x64 and x86 ices are examples
of how that worked for us in PC
computing we never got one of those for
a GPU let's try to get one and while
we're at it let's get one for the USB
controller and the disk controller as
well because if we have those then you
can make an OS very easily every we
could do handmade OS and it would be you
know 30 episodes long or something right
if we did it now it would be god knows
how long
we'd go on forever right to try and get
all the stuff in there
do you feel there's a risk to locking
things into an ice ax that is
potentially still substantially evolving
the average lifespan of an ice ax is
should be substantially longer than an
API and I worry that the rate of
progress would necessarily change for
the worse um so that's a judgment call
and I think you're exactly right so I do
not disagree with that at all
I think it's a judgement call when you
want to move from an ice ax from an API
to an ice ax right I'm arguing the time
is now I'm arguing that we have crossed
the threshold of where the problem is no
longer the hardware innovation it's the
API
it's the cruft right my argument is not
that there aren't drawbacks to switching
to an ice ax my argument is that they
are now less drawbacks to that then
there are from continuing the path we're
going so it's it's a switch right for a
while it was probably clearly the right
decision
not to lock into an ice ax for the
entire system I think we have gotten to
the point where now that trade-off has
changed I think computing the computing
world would be better served going
forward and the future would be brighter
if now we said we know enough about
these problems now that we're willing to
take the hit and it is a hit of
switching to a reliable ice ax going
forwards
Oh sacr the amiga GPU was just a wire
that went across the screen what are you
talk
uh no the Amiga had to separately
programmable graphic specific units one
was the copper unit and maybe that's the
one you're referring to which is the
wire that goes across the screen but the
other was the blitter which is a
programmable memory movement device I
could also do raster ops on it and
Barrel shifting and they had to be
programmed separately it also had a
separate audio processing unit that you
program separately and yet just again
specialized memory also in the Amiga the
Amiga had two types of memory fast DRAM
and chip Ram I won't go into the
specifics of it but it was because of
the access patterns they were on-off
clock cycles so one was it was called
fast Ram because the CPU didn't have to
share the memory bus with the chips for
that memory so the Amiga also had
segmented memory there was memory that
could be accessed by GPU and remember
that couldn't be so again exactly the
same I you are you are drastically
oversimplifying your model of what the
amiga architecture was here's a rack as
part of the doon OS I'm not sure all
right I think we have come to the end I
think we have come to the end of the
lecture and just looking at the chat
real quickly I would summarize what some
of the people are saying
obviously yes switching to and I said
does not stop innovation you can still
innovate on the ice ax as you go forward
it just it does slow it down the reason
it slows it down is because people have
to agree and agreeing on things takes
time right right now Nvidia AMD these
companies can do whatever they want
under the hood to a certain extent right
and so forcing them to now comply with
some level
of specificity in terms of what their
hardware takes in it reduces some of
their ability to change things that's
all so yeah that's that's what I would
that's what I would say obviously the
ice ax yes it does not prevent you from
innovating the x86 x64 so had has been
revved many many many many many many
times right and and they've added I mean
they added Cindy to it right it wasn't
even a Cindy processor at first that at
Cindy they added multi-core they've
added lots of things to the x86 eisah
so yes innovation still occurs it's just
a little harder right and so you don't
want to switch to an ice ax until it's
clear that the benefits of switching to
it are better than the drawbacks and I'm
arguing that they now are whereas they
once probably weren't
got some other questions here the amiga
didn't involve since 1985 why do you
want to freeze PC into toy uh so that's
that's a totally incorrect argument I
apologize but it's laughably bad
the reason the amiga didn't involve
since 1986 was because Commodore
canceled it
they had another chipset architecture it
was a 256 color architecture actually
was much better than the one that they
had the one that they had was a 32
charitably 64 later with half-bright
mode architecture the 4000 eyes did
color thing is a different thing don't
worry about that but they had an 8-bit
per color architecture that was ready to
come out almost immediately after it and
commodore cancelled it because they just
didn't want to pay for that stuff they
weren't interested in that stuff so that
was really a corporate problem and and
had nothing to a nice uh the reason I
say it's a laughable argument is because
we've had a nice ax in the PC space it's
the x86 ice ax and it's gone through
many revisions and added so much stuff
that the design of a PC CPU today is
nothing like it was when that ice that
was introduced so switching to a nice
set absolutely doesn't freeze the design
in any way you still update it very
regularly the difference is just you
lose a little of the speed of your
innovation right you can't just go about
it willy-nilly anymore are you still in
contact with Intel about this no I'm not
that I know of anyway I mean I don't
know what they're doing about it but I
have not talked to them about it in a
while so
all right that's it so I'm gonna wrap it
up now thank you very much for for
joining me and I will post the lecture
on YouTube for those of you who are
interested I will be back tomorrow with
our regularly scheduled programming take
it easy everybody